France.
Now, I know what you're thinking.
If you live in Spain, Italy, Switzerland, Germany,
Belgium, the UK, or God forbid, within France
itself, then you already know that you're not
very far away from France.
And if you live in somewhere like North America,
Asia, Australia or South America, then you know that
you live pretty far away from France.
Except that that second part isn't really true,
because the France I showed you at the
beginning isn't really the entirety of France.
In reality, France is everywhere across
the world, like literally everywhere.
Here's France and North America, here's France and
South America in the Caribbean, including this island
right here, that's divided between France and the
Netherlands, meaning that France and the Netherlands actually
do share a border.
It's just not in Europe, it's in the Caribbean. Here's?
France? Closer to Mexico.
Here's France around Madagascar here's France in the Indian
Ocean and here's France in the Pacific Ocean With
all of these different locations across the globe, you're
probably not as far away from France as you
may have thought if you don't live in Europe.
Inspired by a map I found created by a
reddit user named Alhayle Madame, let's take a look
at how far away you really are from France.
Colored in black is France itself.
Within any of the red zones, you're unfortunately
less than a thousand kilometers away from sovereign
French territory, meaning that you could pretty much
begin hearing French at nearly any minute.
Areas like Nova Scotia, New Brunswick, Quebec, Maine,
Venezuela, Brazil, Madagascar, Mozambique and South Africa are
pretty much all just as far away from
actual sovereign France as Germany or Austria.
Within the orange zone, you're less than two
0 France, which includes the entire northeastern United
States, most of Mexico, the entire Caribbean, and
a whole lot of Africa.
These zones keep radiating out until we're left
with this empty patch here across East Asia.
Within this zone, you're pretty safe because you're
more than seven 0 any French territory, and
it's the furthest possible area away from France
you can get anywhere on the planet.
Spanning across most of China, north Korea, the
Japanese island of Hokkaido, and far eastern Russia.
Now, the various parts of France that exist all
over the world outside of Europe that make all
of this possible are known as overseas France.
And it's this other part of France that makes
France a true global 21st century great power.
Altogether, these various islands and landmasses outside of Europe at
119 386 territory to the French Republic, which is 18%
of France's total land area and is roughly the same
size as either North Korea or Bulgaria.
It's huge, and nearly 3 million people live across
it all, which is about how many people live
in the US state of Kansas, and it represents
about 4% of the entire French population.
Oh, yeah, and that's the thing.
They're all citizens of France and
therefore citizens of the European Union.
By extension as well, which makes all nearly 3 million
of them living in places as far away as the
Caribbean, South America and the Pacific Ocean, all capable of
voting in both French and European elections.
And because of all these territories existing across
the globe, france is actually the country with
the highest number of time zones.
Russia, the world's largest country, spans across only
eleven time zones from west to east.
But France, all with her empire across the world,
actually spans across 13 time zones that are shared
with places as far away as Anchorage, Honolulu, Los
Angeles, New York City, rio de Janeiro, Paris, obviously
Moscow, Dubai, Karachi, Vladivostok, Sydney and Auckland.
It appears that in the 21st century, the sun
continues to never set on the French empire.
But that all just kind of begs another question
why in the world does France even have an
empire that's still this vast outside of Europe?
Well, like every other European power, france also
got in on the overseas empire game over
hundreds of years of progress, with colonies across
Africa, the Middle East and Asia.
But after World War II, the world stopped
being very sympathetic to colonies, and the colonies
of France gradually began declaring their own independence,
culminating with France's final colony in Africa, djibouti,
in the Pacific island of Vanuatu in 1980.
What remains are the final vestiges of the
ancient French colonial empire that simply never desired
independence for themselves and have thus remained a
part of 21st century France.
Some of them are totally uninhabited, or really only
home to seasonal scientists like Clipperton Island here in
the Pacific, the various islands of the southern Antarctic
lands and Adele Land, france's claim over Antarctica that
grants them direct access to the South Pole.
But all the other places are actually inhabited
by permanent populations of people, and some of
them are really hugely important places.
There's Reunion Island, way out here over by Madagascar
in the Indian Ocean, with a population of more
than 8500 people, which alone is more than two
actual EU member states, malta and Luxembourg.
And nearly as much as a third, Cyprus,
nearby Myot, has an additional population of more
than 2700, meaning that there's over a million
French citizens living in the Indian Ocean.
Nearby Madagascar and Africa, both islands are
a fully fledged integral part of France.
They use Euros, and as such, they're the outermost
region of both the European Union and the Eurozone.
Like two distant moons orbiting around their faraway
planet, reunion is one of the few locations
the Europeans discovered across the world that was
actually truly uninhabited back at the time, and
the French acquired it back in the 17th
century and have simply kept it ever since.
But there's other big locations in France's
overseas territories, too, like French Kana, way
over here in South America.
Just like Reunion, French Guyana is an
integral part of France that uses Euros
and is part of the European Union.
Despite bordering Brazil and containing
part of the Amazon rainforest.
This little chunk of Europe and France and South
America isn't really so little, though, because it's nearly
the same size as Austria and one 7th the
size of metropolitan France itself back in Europe, albeit
with a pretty little population of only about 3000
people, which means that the population density throughout is
on a par with Siberia.
That's because nearly 99% of French Guiana is
completely covered by forests, including the Guiana Amazonian
Park, which alone takes up more than 40%
of French Guiana and is, hilariously, the largest
national park of the European Union.
Despite, well, you know, being located in South America,
french Kiana is immensely important to both France and
Europe today because it is the primary launch site
for rockets of the European Space Agency, or Isa.
And it's specifically because of
French Guiana's geographic location.
Look at this map of the world and then
think to yourself, where are the best locations possible
to blast rockets off into space from?
The correct answer is as close as you can
get to the equator across the Earth's center.
And it's because here along this line, the
planet is rotating faster than anywhere else.
Rockets need all the speed they can get in order
to break out of Earth's gravity, and the Earth's natural
rotation speed can give them a muchneeded boost.
Unfortunately for Europe, the equator runs pretty considerably
far away from their continent, which makes blasting
rockets off from there a little more challenging.
But fortunately for Europe, they spent centuries taking over
colonies in other parts of the world, and it
turned out that French Guiana in particular is located
really, really close to the equator.
And so that's how this little chunk of
South America became Europe's most important spaceport.
It's so important that at one point back in
the 1990s, the Guiana Space Center alone accounted for
more than a quarter of French Guiana's entire GDP.
All right, so moving on over to the
Pacific, france retains possessions of hundreds of islands
and atolls across French Polynesia, new Caledonia, wallace
and Fu, Tuna, and Clipperton Island, including the
island of Bora Bora inside of French Polynesia,
which is one of France's most popular tourist
destinations, despite being located on the complete opposite
side of the world from Paris.
But the Pacific part of France carries a
darker secret than the other parts of overseas
France does, because it was here that France
primarily conducted their decadeslong nuclear weapons testing.
Back in 1960, when the French empire still spanned
much more of the globe, france became the fourth
country to successfully test and detonate a nuclear weapon
after the United States, Soviet Union, and United Kingdom.
But they did so initially within
the empty deserts of Algeria.
Awkwardly, at the same time that Algeria was
fighting a war against France for their own
independence, france would go on to detonate a
total of 17 nuclear weapons inside of the
empty deserts of algeria before it became an
independent nation, after which they subsequently refused to
continue allowing France to test their nukes there.
So, still wanting to test their bombs
somewhere, they began looking for alternatives.
One such idea was to begin testing them
on the uninhabited Clipperton Island nearby to Mexico.
But this was ruled out because of the island's intense
level of remoteness, and also Mexico probably would have had
a thing or two to say about it.
Eventually, France settled on continuing their nuclear weapons
testing over in French Polynesia, where a total
of 193 detonations would be carried out in
the Pacific Ocean nearby, which brought France directly
into conflict with nearby New Zealand in 1985.
Back then, the organization Greenpeace orchestrated a campaign against
the continued French nuclear testing in the area with
a boat called the Rainbow Warrior, which was docked
in port outside of Auckland, New Zealand.
The ship was about to depart towards French Polynesia
to protest against a planned French nuclear test when
two undercover French operatives secretly snuck on board, planted
a bomb and then blew the ship apart.
The explosions sank the ship and killed
a Greenpeace photographer who was on board.
The French agents were quickly apprehended afterwards by
the New Zealand police and were each sentenced
to ten years in prison for manslaughter.
They would ultimately only serve for two years
before being freed by the French government.
Many political figures, especially in New Zealand, have
consistently referred to the action ever since as
an incident of French state sponsored terrorism.
And France would ultimately agree to pay 816
million dollars in damages to Greenpeace, along with
six $5 million to the New Zealand government
as an apology, and a further half a
million dollars to the photographer's family.
As compensation, France would continue testing nuclear weapons
in Polynesia for eleven more years, until 1996,
the year of their final detonation.
And ever since, they've switched to using computer
simulations for their nuclear weapons testing instead.
And today, France maintains an arsenal of approximately
300 nuclear weapons, the third largest arsenal in
the world after the United States and Russia.
So that was one reason that France
kept much of their overseas empire.
But overall, the biggest reason why France maintains the
overseas empire up to the present is because of
the control that it gives France and the European
Union as a proxy over the world's oceans.
You see, under the terms of the United Nations
Convention on the Law of the Sea, or Unclose,
any country may claim an exclusive economic zone, or
EEZ, of the water surrounding their sovereign coastline.
The country making the claim retains the sole
and exclusive legal authority for all fishing, drilling,
mining and all other economic activities.
And because of their hundreds of islands and territories
that are scattered across all the corners of the
Earth, france actually possesses the modern world's largest EEZ
and therefore the largest maritime territory of any 21st
century nation, ahead of even the United States.
And Australia.
France's EEZ spans nearly eleven 7 million ocean
across the Bay of Biscay, the Indian Ocean,
while almost completely surrounding Madagascar, huge blotches of
the Pacific Ocean, and even a tiny little
sliver here, just south of Canada.
These small islands are St Pierre and Microsoft, and
despite being located right next to Newfoundland in Canada,
they're a part of France and home to more
than 60 French citizens who all use Euros.
They are the small final remaining vestiges of
the old colonial new France in the Americas,
and they have a fascinating history of control.
When France was defeated in the Seven Years War
back in 1763, they were forced to cede all
of their North American possessions over to the British.
But since the British continued to grant
the French fishing rights along the Newfoundland
coast, they allowed them to keep the
tiny islands as a little fishing outpost.
When France supported America during the American
Revolution, burton invaded the islands, raised the
settlement, and exiled the entire French population
back to European France.
Out of spite, Burton tried to bring in British
settlers to repopulate the islands, but then the French
came back and sacked the British colony.
Eventually, the British gave the islands back
to France once again in 18 two.
But then after war with Napoleon erupted, they reoccupied
them again the very next year in 18 three.
When the Napoleonic Wars were concluded eleven years later,
in 1814, the British once again gave the islands
back to France, but then occupied them again in
1815, when Napoleon briefly returned to power in France,
and then gave them back to France yet again
after he was defeated after Waterloo for good, and
they've been French ever since.
During the First World War, all of the men
on the islands were drafted, and about 400 went
on to serve on the Western Front in Europe,
where a quarter of them would die.
When the topic of EEZ came up in the
1970s, france initially claimed a huge one for the
tiny little islands that severely interrupted nearby Canada's EEZ,
which led to a very long legal dispute between
both countries over fishing rights.
It was only eventually settled in 1992
when France accepted the significantly smaller and
narrower boundaries of the current EEZ here.
But it's still kind of weird, because now the
French control this zone where they're the only ones
who are allowed to fish, and it's completely surrounded
by the zone where the Canadians are the only
ones who are allowed to fish.
So Canadian fishermen have to always move around it,
and local French fishermen are always confined within it.
But when zooming back out again to see
the full picture, france's oceanic territory, all combined
across the world, is larger than the entirety
of the European continent itself, and France possesses
8% of the entire world's EEZ areas, despite
the fact that France itself only possesses 00:40.
5% of the world's land, and only
zero 84% of the world's population.
If you were to combine both land and maritime
area for every country in the world, then France
all of a sudden ranks as the world's fifth
largest country, beating out places like Brazil, China, India,
or Indonesia, which is frankly just ridiculous.
And it all gives France and by extension,
the European Union an enormous global geopolitical advantage.
When also factoring in Spain's, Portugal, the Netherlands,
and Denmark's overseas territories, the European Union's collective
EEZ enables it to dominate the entire Baltic,
control nearly the entire Mediterranean and the eastern
North Atlantic, and have outposts across every ocean
and every corner of the globe.
After the United Kingdom and the United States,
france even further maintains the third largest amount
of overseas military bases outside of their home
territory, with bases all across their overseas possessions
in South America, the Caribbean, Indian, and Pacific
Oceans, with even further bases across many of
their former colonies in Africa, like Djibouti, Ivory
Coast, Cabon, Senegal, Mali, Chad, and Niger.
Additional bases across the Middle East in
Syria, Iraq, Jordan, and the UAE, and
a final two more inside of Germany.
Altogether, France maintains a force of more than 360
soldiers deployed to these territories across the world.
And ever since 2001, the French
have initiated military interventions across these
nine countries on two separate continents.
The presence of these French military bases and soldiers
all across the world, from South America to Africa,
the Middle East and the Pacific, gives the French
a very similar capability to the United States.
They can project power and deploy military
assets at a moment's notice to counter
almost any threat anywhere on the planet.
So when you look at a map like
this, you realize that the global French, and
therefore the global European empire is very much
still alive and well in the 21st century.
And as a result, France and Europe are probably a
lot closer to you than you may have realized.
But something else you may have not realized yet
is just how much you're probably overpaying for your
current cell phone plan and how much you could
save by switching over to Ting.
I personally switched over to Ting
myself a few months ago. And why?
Well, because of this.
Yep, that's actually a real phone bill that
I received from my old carrier right before
I made my switch earlier this year.
But Ting Mobile has three different plans to choose
from to make sure that never happens again.
Unlimited talk and text starts at just $10,
and then data is $5 a gigabyte.
Or you can just get their unlimited plan for just $45.
They've also got other plans with five or 12GB of data.
But regardless, the point is that you can get the
same service you have right now with the same phone
number you have right now for much less money.
So if you've ever got a bill
like mine, your service probably won't change.
It's pretty much a no brainer, but what should
really seal the deal is that when you click
the button that's on your screen right now or
follow the link that's down in the description, you'll
get a totally free $25 credit, enough for an
entire month of service on some of their plans.
And signing up their re helps to support
real life lore at the same time.
And as always, thank you so much for watching.