This is Mexico City.
It is currently the 6th largest city in the entire
world, with nearly 3 million more people than New York.
And it's by far the largest
Spanishspeaking city in the world.
Mexico City is high on the list of
the world's most significant, significant and influential cities.
But it has one enormous and one very old problem.
The entire city is sinking into the ground
at an insanely alarming rate, with some parts
at about half a meter every single year.
That is so fast that many geologists have predicted
most of Mexico City will sink about 20 meters
beneath where it currently stands by the end of
the 21st century, with some particularly heavy hit areas
sinking more than 30 meters.
Imagine your house sinking 30 meters
beneath where it is today.
That would be a hole so deep, if you stood at
the top and jumped in, it would take about two and
a half seconds for you to hit the bottom.
Unfortunately for millions of Mexicans, this is exactly
what's going to happen to them very slowly
over the course of the next few decades.
And it's all because humans are really,
really prone to choosing objectively, terrible locations
to place their cities in.
Mexico City, in particular, has some of the worst
geography stats of any major city in the world.
And this is why let's rewind the geographical and
historical clock back a little over 700 years ago.
Back then, the region's geography and
reality was very different from today.
The city didn't exist, and in its place was a
large lake called Lake Texcoco, wedged in a large valley
surrounded by high mountains and volcanoes on all sides.
Legend has it that for 100 years
before this, the nomadic Mexican tribe awaited
the fulfillment of an ancient prophecy.
They would eventually settle down and build the greatest
city in the world, where the location would be
determined wherever they saw an eagle eating a snake
in its beak while perched atop a cactus.
Eventually, this prophecy would be realized when the Mexican
finally saw this exact vision in the most unlikely
of places for the greatest city the world would
ever see a small, unpopulated and swampy island right
here in the middle of Lake Texcoco.
But undeterred by the formidable terrain, the
Mexico kept true to their prophecy and
began building their great city.
And over the next two centuries, this small swampy
island was continually enlarged by landfills and floating gardens
until it eventually evolved into Tenochtitlan, the capital of
the Aztec empire and one of the largest cities
in the entire medieval world.
By the time the Spanish arrived in 1519, tenochtitlan was
five times the size of London under Henry VIII.
And at the time, considering the Aztecs
position on the Tech tree, the city's
geography didn't actually seem so bad.
Without being fortunate enough to have any pack animals like
horses or oxen, and without having discovered any practical use
of the wheel, the Aztecs had no other means available
to them for transporting goods and conducting trade than by
moving across the water on boats.
Tenochtitlan's various canals easily
facilitated this role.
And when you combine that with a complex series
of dams they built that provided abundant clean drinking
water, extremely rich in fertile soil and a highly
defensible position surrounded by a literal moat, it's no
wonder that the city became Mesoamerica's most successful.
That is, until the Spanish and Cortez arrived in
1519, tenochtitlan was put under a brutal siege and
under Cortez's direct orders, the Aztec dams across the
lake were destroyed in order to turn Lake Tex
coco salty and deny the Aztecs inside of any
access to clean drinking water without their drinking water.
And after a virulent smallpox epidemic, the
Aztecs inside withered away and the Spanish
conquered and subsequently raised the city almost
completely to the ground, brick by brick.
By the end of the 16th century, the
once great city of Tenochtitlan's population had declined
by over 90% and atop the ruins the
Spaniards founded their new settlement called Mexico City.
And this is when the big problems really began.
The Spaniards never rebuilt the Aztec dams
and dykes and replaced them with more
familiar streets and public squares instead.
On the plus side, this allowed them to gradually reclaim
more and more land from the lake to make more
space for Mexico City's growing population and buildings.
But on the other side, this meant that the city was
expanding into a swamp that was surrounded by a lake without
any dam to keep out any of the lake's water.
Flooding therefore became a constant problem for Mexico
City as it expanded and grew, including one
particularly bad case in 1629 when the city
flooded for five straight years.
The Spanish Crown even discussed moving
the location of the city to
a bit less geographically problematic place.
But evidently they thought eh, they just decided to stay
and drain the lake even more and even more instead.
Under the Aztecs, Tenochtitlant's population was around 4000
at its peak and was basically just a
small but very dense dot within Lake Texcoco.
By 1900, the population here was actually pretty
much the same, but the 20th century would
see the city's population absolutely skyrocket.
By 1950 the city had grown to cover 30 sq.
Mi and was home to over 3 million people.
And today Mexico City has grown from there to
cover an area of approximately three 0 sq.
Mi and with nearly 22 million people.
This enormous development in just 100 years has
effectively wiped out any trace of the former
waters of Lake Tex cocoa and covered it
instead with a lake of concrete and it's
wreaked total havoc on the valley's environment.
Mexico City is in a region that
receives even more rainfall than infamously rainy
places like London or Seattle.
But despite that, the city perpetually struggles
to provide enough water for her citizens.
Without the waters of Lake Texcoco, the city has
been forced to drill deeper and deeper into the
belowground aquifers in her ever desperate quest for water.
The problem here is that the land beneath mexico
city is an ancient soft clay lake bed.
And as mexico city drills for more and
more water, the clay weakens and crumbles.
The water pressure within the aquifer supports the soil above
it, which in turn supports the city above it.
However, as the water is drained
and removed, the soil above compacts.
This compaction, combined with the lower water pressure pushing
from beneath, will slowly cause the city to sink
over time and rainwater can't easily get into the
aquifers to replenish them because the land above is
now absolutely covered in the concrete sprawling chaos of
the world's 6th largest city.
And as a result, mexico city is
trapped in a vicious geologic cycle.
As the population grows, the
demand for water further increases.
But without the waters of the natural lake,
she is then left with no other choice
but to drill deeper into the belowground aquifers,
which reduces the soil stability above and leads
to the city sinking even further and further.
With the increased development above from the
increasing population, rainwater can't get in to
replenish the aquifers and the soil's instability
continues to get worse.
Climate change even further exacerbates these already dire
conditions, since more heat and more drought in
the region inevitably also means more evaporation and
even more demand for the already scarce water
supply, leading to even further drilling and of
course, even further sinking.
Mexico city of course, knows all of this,
and through a complex series of canals and
pipes, they now import about 40% of their
water supply from other regions of Mexico.
However, these canals and pipes are wildly inefficient.
The constantly shifting elevation causes pipes below the
ground to routinely crack and burst, while the
struggling city government is rarely capable of mounting
any kind of significant repairs.
And as a result of that, for every one gallon of
water that is pumped into the pipes of mexico city, more
than one third of it will simply be lost.
And the energy that's required to pump all of that
water up to a city that's a mile and a
half high in elevation in the mountains is more than
what the entire city of puebla consumes.
A city with roughly the
same population as philadelphia.
So as a result, mexico city faces water shortages
as if it were in the middle of a
desert, despite receiving more rainfall than london.
And there isn't any easy or obvious solution
for them to get out of this.
But the city's thinking problem affects far
more than just the water supply, since
it affects some areas worse than others.
Roads will suddenly buckle and wobble.
Buildings tip over and look
like they're about to collapse.
The metro system in some areas will resemble
more of a roller coaster, while the destruction
caused by earthquakes is greatly amplified.
Mexico city is unfortunately located within a seismically active
zone and with most of the city's core located
on the weak and sulty clay lake bed.
The soil will often behave more like a liquid
during an earthquake, causing the buildings above to be
even more greatly damaged than they otherwise would be.
This is how, in 1085, the Mexico City earthquake caused
such catastrophic damage and loss in life to the city.
Mexico City's rapid and unexpected population explosion
in the 20th century caused other unnatural
problems to crop up as well.
By 1992, Mexico City was home to more than
500 industries and more than 4 million motor vehicles.
Due to the city's high elevation a mile and a
half above sea level its oxygen levels are 25% lower
when compared to a city that is precisely at sea
level and therefore fuels don't combust as efficiently further.
Mexico City is located within a high
valley that's surrounded by tall mountains which
effectively keeps pollutants and exhaust trapped within
without any place to go.
This all meant that by 1992, the UN had
labeled Mexico City as the world's most polluted city.
But 30 years later, after a variety of methods,
mexico City has managed to get their air pollution
levels down in the valley to about the same
level seen in Los Angeles today.
But air pollution continues to be the 8th leading
cause of death within Mexico and causes about one
in every 17 deaths in the country.
For the Aztecs seven centuries ago, settling
on an island in Lake Texcoco not
only fulfilled an ancient prophecy but made
perfect geographic sense with their understanding of
technology and limited population at the time.
In the current day, though, it's one
of the worst locations imaginable for the
industrialized world's 6th largest city and has
caused countless problems for centuries.
But it's too late now since pushing Mexico
City somewhere else just isn't really feasible.
Mexico City's countless geographic problems are just a fact of
life now and something that has to be lived with
because in the end, nature will always win.
Mexico's City's struggle against her environment has been
one of the most massive and intimidating projects
that humanity has had to have ever undertaken.
Maybe you're watching this and you've got your own
project or personal goal that you've been meaning to
start recently that you think is similarly challenging.
And as a result, you're unsure that you have the
skills required to go about doing it just yet.
Whatever it is you're wanting to do, whether it's
getting started, creating your own YouTube channel, making videos
like this one or any other big project, the
best place to get started is over on skillshare.
Five years ago, I was in
the exact same position as you.
The project that I wanted to
start was my YouTube channel.
But I had absolutely no idea what I
was doing or how to even get started.
I never went to school for animation or art
and I doubted my abilities to ever create anything
that anyone would actually want to watch.
In the end, I had to teach myself over the
years by watching tutorial videos online here on YouTube.
But eventually I got introduced to Skillshare,
and through targeted classes like this one
called Make Animated YouTube Videos by Evan
from Polymatter, who has since become my
friend, I accelerated my learning even further.
The classes on Skillshare are from real professionals who
have tons of experience in what they're talking about,
who guide you step by step through the process,
and all of it is specifically curated for learning
without any ads getting between you and your goals.
If you want to start creating your own videos
here on YouTube, the perfect place to begin with
would be the class YouTube Success Script, Shoot and
Edit with MKBHD, taught by none other than Marquez
Brownlee or MKBHD here on YouTube.
Or maybe you just want to improve
your own productivity and motivation in general.
My friend Ali Abdull has the
perfect option for that as well.
With his class productivity.
Master class principles and tools
to boost your productivity.
But the greatest thing about Skillshare is that when you
become a member, you can take any of these classes
as well as thousands of others on nearly any subject
you can imagine, ranging from animation and graphic design to
web development and drawing, any of which can help you
find a new passion, help you get ahead in school,
or give you the skills needed for career advancement.
It's the absolute perfect activity for whenever you have a
lot of free time or when you're staying at home.
And with its varying difficulty levels, it's still
great whether you're a beginner or an expert.
And best of all, you can watch absolutely all
of these classes and get started today with an
entire month long trial completely for free, by clicking
the button that's on your screen right now, or
by being one of the first 10 people who
follow the link down below in my description.
By doing this, you can achieve all of
your own personal learning goals, and it really
helps support reallife lore at the same time.
So go ahead and check them out by clicking the button.
And as always, thank you for watching.