Las Vegas is one of the most
well known cities anywhere in the world.
Tens of millions of people visit it every single
year who contribute to making it the third most
visited city in the United States by foreign tourists.
Just behind New York and Miami, las Vegas
receives so many foreign tourists that it beats
out many other major tourist hotspot cities across
the world, like Los Angeles, Chicago, Shanghai, Barcelona,
Berlin, Vienna and even Venice.
In order to accommodate all of these visitors, las
Vegas possesses a truly impressive hospitality arsenal of around
1500 hotel rooms, which is more than any other
city on the planet has got.
And this is despite the fact that Las Vegas
itself is a relatively young city, having only existed
for a tad longer than a century, and with
a relatively small metropolitan population of only little more
than two 2 million people, which only ranks it
as the 26th largest city in the United States.
But Las Vegas's size and age are
irrelevant factors to the massive volumes of
tourists who arrive here every single year.
For them, they almost all come for just
one single thing vegas legendary reputation as the
entertainment capital of the world and the greatest
playground for adults anywhere on the earth.
Along with Louisiana, the state of Nevada, where
Las Vegas is located, is the only American
state to a fully legalized casino gambling statewide,
which has long caused Vegas to be almost
synonymous with gambling and casinos.
Around eight in every ten visitors to the city will
gamble at one of the numerous casinos while they're there,
and at an average of around $600 a person, while
slightly more than half of all visitors will attend one
of the many shows hosted in the city as well.
Altogether, these tourists visiting the city generally contribute more
than $100 billion per year to the Nevada state
economy and place Las Vegas as one of the
top travel destinations in the world.
But the strangest aspect of the city for me.
As someone who spent much of their childhood
growing up in Nevada with more visits to
Las Vegas than I can even count.
Is the fact that all of this outrageous
entertainment and access for tens of millions of
people all seemingly exists precisely where it shouldn't
in the middle of the driest and least
hospitable desert of the North American continent.
The Mojave Desert.
This is the same desert that includes Death Valley,
after all, the ominously and appropriately named valley, located
just a two hour drive from the Las Vegas
strip that recorded the hottest temperature ever measured on
the surface of the earth a little more than
a century ago in 1913.
At 134 degrees Fahrenheit.
Or 57 degrees Celsius.
The Mojave Desert is so dry that the area
around Las Vegas itself only receives an average of
around four inches of rainfall per year.
Which is even less rain than Timbuktu receives in Mali.
At the southern edge of the sahara Desert in 2020.
Las Vegas set a still standing record of going 224
entire straight days without a single drop of rainfall.
And the reason for Las Vegas extreme dryness is
almost entirely geographical the Mojave Desert itself is located
entirely east of the towering Sierra Nevada mountains of
California with peaks as high as Mount Whitney at
14 505ft the highest point anywhere in the contiguous
48th United States and a mere 85 miles away
as the crow flies from the aforementioned Death Valley
the lowest point on the North American continent at
282ft beneath sea level.
These towering mountains block most of the moisture that
blows into North America from the westerly winds of
the Pacific and they therefore cast what's known as
a rain shadow across their east where the moisture
coming in from the Pacific fails to penetrate into.
Of course.
Las Vegas itself is located directly within this rain
shadow cast by the Sierra Nevada but it's also
located within a valley here that's surrounded by even
further mountain ranges on every side.
Some of which soar up to ten 0ft in elevation
and block even more moisture from blowing into the city
with the wind from beyond and the nearest significant river
and source of fresh water to this valley.
The Colorado is around 30 miles away from it in short.
This valley was never historically a very attractive
location to build even a settlement and much
less a modern metropolis of two and a
quarter million people and as a result.
It was basically nothing of any more significance
than sparsely populated desert for thousands of years
until the very beginning of the 20th century
when the city of Las Vegas was officially
founded in 19 five and incorporated in 1911.
But for the next several decades afterwards, vegas would
remain relatively sleepy and quiet until 1931 when two
major things happened that would change the region's demographic
destiny forever afterwards with a tiny population of only
940 people statewide, nevada was by far the least
populous state in the country at the time.
With less than half the population of the Netsley's
populous state Wyoming reeling from the economic fallout of
the Great Depression and struggling to find anyone who
is willing to invest in their tiny state economy.
The Nevada state government decided on a bold course of
action they became the first US state to legalize nearly
every form of gambling in order to bring in at
least some kind of economic relief to their state.
And perhaps even more importantly, 1931 also marks the beginning
of the construction of the Hoover Dam on the Colorado
River just 30 miles away from the city.
And perhaps even more importantly, never before in human
history had such a monolithic structure ever been built
with concrete thousands of laborers moved in and worked
tirelessly for years to finish the job and at
least 115 of them lost their lives trying.
But with the thousands of new workers coming
into the town for the damn construction came
higher demands for things like entertainment and amenities.
And with the recent legalization of casino gambling,
the genesis for Las Vegas's status as the
entertainment capital of the world was born.
When the dam was finished in 1936, it created
the largest water reservoir in the entire United States,
just behind it in the form of Lake Mead
and granted the southwestern United States the ability to
generate enormous amounts of electricity through hydropower.
The Colorado River is ideally suited for hydroelectric
power generation, owing to its large flow and
steep gradient descending from its source high up
in the Rocky Mountains of Colorado towards the
lower elevations of the Mojave and Sonoran Deserts.
With massive volumes of water pumped to the
city directly from Lake Mead and massive amounts
of electricity from the dam, investment finally began
pouring into Las Vegas and its unique entertainment
industry following the Second World War, and the
population began to steadily increase.
By 1960, Las Vegas had finally overtaken reno to
become Nevada's most populous city with 640 people, and
the population would roughly double from there over the
next decade to more than 1250 people by 1970,
more people than lived in the entirety of Nevada
just 30 years previously.
From then, back in 1940, between 19 92,000,
the population of Las Vegas roughly doubled again.
And by the close of the 20th century, las Vegas
had earned the distinction of being the most populous city
in North America that was founded within the same century,
just like Chicago had been during the 19th century.
But as Las Vegas fortunes and population continued to
soar, so too did the demand in the region
for the area's sparse supplies of water.
With its crippling lack of rainfall, the population of Las
Vegas and southern Nevada is overwhelmingly dependent upon Lake Mead
and the Colorado River that feeds it from the snow
melt of the Rocky Mountains, accounting for some 90% of
all the city's fresh water today.
Back in the 1920s, prior to the construction
of the Hoover Dam, the seven American states
that controlled territory within the Colorado Rivers Basin
agreed to the Colorado River Compact an agreement
the divided control of the waters within the
basin amongst all seven of the states.
The upper space of Colorado, Utah, Wyoming and New
Mexico would be entitled to roughly half of the
Colorado River's water, while the lower states of California,
Arizona and Nevada would be entitled to the other
half, with nearly 59% of that half going to
California, 37% of Arizona and just 4% to Nevada.
But the realities of the 1920s were
very different from the realities of today.
One of the biggest concerns of the agreement,
both then and now, was the expanding population
in the southwest, particularly in Southern California, and
the resulting increased demand over time for water
in the lower basin states.
At the same time, Las Vegas wasn't even really
a factor at all back in the 1920s, with
a population of less than 30 people.
But with a modern population well in excess of
over 2 million, nevada has been looking for an
increased share in the river's water now for decades.
But today there are more than 40 million people who
depend on the Colorado River for their water supply, and
Las Vegas is only a small fraction of that.
And at the same time, the Colorado River's water
has actually been greatly over allocated for decades now,
because the original estimates of the compact back in
the 1920s suggested that the river had an annual
average flow of about 17 and a half million
acre feet of water that reached the lower basin
states of Arizona, Nevada and California.
However, these estimates back at the time were based
on just the past 30 years of records going
back to the 1890s, which were all the records
that the people of the 1920s actually had available.
And modern 21st century studies of tree rings in
the area have revealed that those 30 years of
records they used just so happened to probably be
the wettest period in the American Southwest any time
in the past five to twelve centuries.
In other words, the authors of the 1920s
era compact were grossly misinformed on the actual
historical average levels of water within the river.
And more water has been being allocated
to the states around it than actually
exists within the river almost ever since.
And then climate change, decreased rates of
snowfall in the Rocky Mountains, and droughts
have been making everything much worse.
And the situation has now gotten so bad that the
Colorado River today rarely even has enough flow left in
it to make it to its natural delta in the
Gulf of California in Mexico, where the once rich natural
environment has almost completely died there and dried up.
This also means that Lake Mead, itself
the source of most of modern Las
Vegas freshwater, is rapidly shrinking in size.
Last month, in June of 2022, the reservoir hit
a new all time low after losing nearly 180ft
of depth over just the past 20 years.
If the levels drop by another 100ft,
the Hoover Dam will no longer be
capable of producing any hydroelectric power.
But as it has always done now for
the past century, las Vegas is rapidly learning
how to adapt to this changing environment.
And fascinatingly, despite being well renowned as a city
of tremendous successes, las Vegas is one of the
most water efficient cities in the entire world because
they have no other choice but to be.
Remember when I said that Nevada is only
allocated 4% of the lower Colorado River's water?
That amounts to just around 300,000 acre feet
of water today, which isn't really a lot
when considering the California takes more than 14
times that amount from the river.
But the catch is that so long as the water
is returned back to the river, it doesn't actually count
against the state in terms of total consumption.
This loophole means that the Southern Nevada Water Authority
will usually draw around 4450 acre feet of water
from Lake Mead during a normal year, or about
40% more than they're technically allotted for.
But since the city is capable of cleaning and
returning around 2200 acre feet of water back to
Lake Me during the same year, Nevada's total consumption
from the river is usually more like just 2250
acre feet and well beneath their total allotment.
In order to achieve this incredible rate of water
recycling, the city of Las Vegas has enacted a
number of ingenious, policy and engineering decisions.
The city has been designed in such a way that
every last drop of water that ends up being used
indoors gets cleaned and recycled directly back to Lake Mead.
You could quite literally turn on every single shower
and every single sink in every hotel room in
the city, and it wouldn't ever consume any more
water because it would all just flow through the
city sewers directly to water treatment plants and then
directly return all clean back to Lake Mead for
future use and further watering.
Lawns within the city limits was strictly limited
to just a single day a week.
And largely because of its focus on sustainable desert
design, las Vegas actually managed to reduce their total
water consumption dramatically by 26% over the past 20
years since 2002, despite having added an additional 7500
new residents to the total population of the city
over the same time period.
And they aren't finished reducing
their water consumption either.
The first type of law of its kind in the United
States, las Vegas banned nonfunctional and decorative grass in the city
last year in 2021, to save even more water.
Grass has been getting torn out across city
owned property across Las Vegas ever since, and
it's going to make an enormous difference.
1 grass consumes 73 gallons of water a year
in order to keep alive, while more drought tolerant
desert landscaping only consumes 18 gallons a year.
City officials are spending millions of dollars
trying to convince current homeowners to tear
out their grassy lawns and replace them
with more water friendly desert landscaping options.
The Southern Nevada Water Authority believes that these simple
landscaping measures favoring sustainable desert landscaping over nonfunctional grass
will save around nine and a half billion gallons
of water a year, which is nearly 10% of
Las Vegas total water supply.
In a lot of senses, Las Vegas is
the model city for the rest of the
southwestern United States as the region faces increasingly
harsher drought conditions and decreasing water supplies.
As the American government just recently issued its first
ever declared water shortage for the Colorado River this
year, it has cut water allocations to all the
states along the river, including Nevada's, from 300,000 acre
feet to just 2790 acre feet, which, when factoring
in the rate of Las Vegas incredible rate of
water recycling, is still enough to meet current demand.
But for how much longer?
Many climate experts are warning that water levels
within the Colorado basin will likely continue to
drop over the next several decades.
When combined with the ever increasing demand for
water from the still growing population across southern
Nevada, Arizona, and Southern California, the life for
the desert communities here are almost certainly going
to continue growing ever more challenging from a
water security perspective.
The fact simply is that in the future, the other
cities of the American Southwest and everywhere else in the
world who will struggle with water supplies in the near
future should look to Las Vegas for their inspiration of
a city well designed to cope with the challenges of
21st century climate change in the middle of one of
Earth's least hospitable desert environments.
For if life can be sustained for millions
of people and tens of millions of visitors
here through decades of clever design and foresight,
it can also be achieved elsewhere.
Now, a major reason that I was so excited
to make a video covering this topic is because
I knew that I could get all kinds of
spectacular footage of Las Vegas and the Colorado River
without actually having to go travel and visit them
myself by simply visiting my stock footage provider instead.
Storyblocks, without any exaggeration since the very first
real life lore videos that I created more
than six years ago now, Storyblocks has always
been the first place that I've always gone.
To find footage for all of my videos, they offer
an unlimited subscription so that you can download and use
as much as you need for an annual price.
That's lower than what many other providers
charge for just a single clip.
And beyond that unlimited subscription, storyblocks also
offers an entirely royalty free library, meaning
that you can use anything from the
library for any commercial or personal use.
And Storyblocks offers far more
than just footage and templates.
They also provide music, images,
sound effects, and much more.
If you're already a creator or you're wanting
to become one, I can absolutely tell you
from my more than six years of experience
now, as their customer, that Storyblocks is an
absolutely critical resource for you to have.
I genuinely don't think I know of
a single full time creator who doesn't
already have a subscription with them.
So if you'd like to get started with them as
well, click the button that's here on screen right now,
or head over to Storyblocks.com RealLifeLore to sign up.
And by doing so, you'll also be greatly supporting my
channel at the same time while you're at it.
And as always, thank you so much for watching.