This is the United States.
This is Louisiana and this is New Orleans.
And without constant human intervention,
this city literally wouldn't exist.
It has perhaps the worst geographic location of any
major city in America, and there are there are
countless reasons why that are all named water.
New Orleans is a city that is almost
completely surrounded by water on all sides.
To the north is Lake Pontia train.
In the center is the Mississippi River, and
to the south and east is the ever
encroaching seawater from the Gulf of Mexico.
To make matters even worse, 65% of the New
Orleans metropolitan area is located either at or beneath
sea level, a greater percentage than even the Netherlands,
which is only about a third beneath sea level.
This means that when you take a look at New
Orleans from the side, it's effectively just a big bowl
that's surrounded on nearly all of its edges by water.
And whenever the water tips over the sides from
either the river or the lake, the city drowns.
And to make matters even more severe, new Orleans
placement directly at the Gulf of Mexico's edge makes
it the most frequent target of hurricanes in America.
With an 11% risk of being
slammed by one every single year.
Hurricanes make the flooding problem
in the city even worse.
But that's still not all.
Due to a variety of reasons that
I'll get into later in the video.
Louisiana's coastline has been losing the war against the
water for the greater part of a century now.
Over the past 100 years, 2000 sq mi of land
has been conquered by the ocean in Louisiana south.
That's twice the size of Luxembourg.
And the ocean's advances are accelerating to the tune
of about one football field worth of land every
hour, 24 hours a day, 365 days a year.
This is putting the ocean and its waters dangerously
closer and closer to New Orleans every single hour,
and it's placing the city on a time bomb.
Southern Louisiana is slowly drowning.
And it ultimately begs the question, since nature seems
to think that settling a city here was such
an obviously terrible idea, then why didn't humans?
The answer to that is because, of course, it never
really seemed like a bad location until fairly recently.
In fact, for most of America's and even
humanities history, the area around New Orleans was
without a doubt one of the most important
locations on the entire planet to control.
Take a look at the map of the world.
Pretend that you've just begun a game of civilization where
you're low on the tech tree and look at where
the best locations to build a wealthy city are going
to be on the North American continent.
I would argue for the area around
New Orleans being historically the number one
pick for one incredibly important reason.
Despite all the risks of flooding and natural disasters,
new Orleans sits near the mouth of the Mississippi
River and by setting up a choke point here,
one can fully control all of the trade and
transportation flowing into and out of it.
This is vital because by entering the
Mississippi here, you can travel throughout almost
the entirety of the north American interior
by way of the Mississippi river basin.
Every single one of these creeks, streams, and rivers
eventually all flow into the Mississippi and find their
way down to new Orleans and the ocean.
Until the advent of modern technology like railroads,
planes, or highways, it was rivers and waterways
all across the world which served as humanity's
high speed transportation and trade arteries.
And the Mississippi is the biggest and the most
important system of them all anywhere on the planet.
In fact, the greater Mississippi river basin has
more kilometers of navigable internal waterways than the
entire rest of the world all combined has.
This fact is enormous because it was basically
the world's largest natural transportation system on any
continent that today flows through 31 US.
States and two Canadian provinces.
This system literally connected almost the entire north
American continental mainland to the atlantic ocean and
the rest of the world from there.
And all of it could effectively be dominated
by whoever controlled just this small choke point
right near the entrance to the Mississippi river.
The french were the first big empire
who recognized this area's immense strategic value.
And a little over 300 years ago, they founded the
small settlement of new Orleans here along the river's curve,
where it created a natural levee about one and a
half meters above sea level, comparatively higher than the surrounding
swamplands that were beneath sea level.
The initial small settlement fared well against floods
and hurricanes, and a century later found itself
under the possession of a new and future
global empire the United States.
The Mississippi river and all of its
various tributaries stretching as far as denver,
minneapolis, des moines, omaha, kansas city, and
Oklahoma city, enabled millions of American settlers
to venture out and conquer the west.
And they could reach all of these places via
new Orleans, and all of the goods they would
end up producing would flow back to new Orleans.
As America expanded westwards, the Mississippi river became
roughly the dividing line between east and west
within the continental states, and the importance of
new Orleans became ever more apparent.
If any enemy power were to gain control of
it, they could shut the entire river down and
effectively cut America in half and block all of
the massive volume of trade flowing down it from
the dozens of other states that were making new
Orleans one of the wealthiest cities in the world.
In fact, by the 1840s, new Orleans was America's
third biggest city, behind only New York and Baltimore.
And by the time of the civil war, it
was easily the south's largest and most important city.
River boats and barges easily transported luxury
goods like cotton from southern states like
Mississippi and industrial goods from northern factories
up in Illinois, Indiana and Ohio.
And New Orleans was at the
zenith of her power and influence.
But after the Civil War, the
city's fortunes would dramatically reverse.
The invention of new technologies like the
railroad introduced new transportation and trade routes
that largely bypassed New Orleans location.
Down in the southeast, as more and more railroads
and later interstate highways for trucks and cars and
airports for planes were built, the crucial importance of
the Mississippi and its various riverways diminished.
By the 20th century, the Mississippi no longer had
a monopoly on middle America's transportation and trade.
And in New Orleans's, monopoly over admits to
that system no longer mattered quite as much.
By World War II, New Orleans had plummeted from
America's third largest city to only her 15th.
And despite reaching the height of her population in
1960 with about 6200 people, she was no longer
even the biggest city in the American south.
With cities like Dallas and Houston having passed her
up with their much more rapid growth thereafter, new
Orleans would enter into a slow and steady decline.
With economic opportunity moving on to
other parts of the country.
New Orleans lost 18% of our population
in only 30 years, between 1000 972,000.
Faced with a serious demographic crisis like this, the leaders
of the city at the time decided that they needed
to encourage more growth by developing more land.
But the problem with that is that New Orleans was
founded as an 18th century outpost and its expansion from
those borders into a modern, sprawling city was always doomed
to be severely limited by simple geography.
As New Orleans developed around her colonial era core
that was on some of the highest ground available
in the area, she had no other choice but
to expand further into the swampy and flood prone
lands that were closer to and eventually even beneath
sea level, which was a dangerous decision.
In order to develop the swampland even further,
the city began draining out all of the
water, which caused the soil beneath to compact
and led to the modern city above sinking.
Today, parts of New Orleans are sinking by as
much as 5 year, and when you remember that
most of the city is already beneath sea level
and right next to several major bodies of water,
you can understand why this is all catastrophically dangerous.
What makes matters even worse is the fact that
sea levels are only rising as time goes on,
which is making the bowl shape of New Orleans,
surrounded by precarious water on all sides, more and
more dangerous as the 21st century continues.
With all that in mind, let's analyze
all of New Orleans contemporary geographic issues.
First up, Lake Ponter train.
I want you to look at this map
of the elevation levels throughout New Orleans.
And now I want you to look at
this map that shows the areas with the
most severe flooding from Hurricane Katrina in 2005.
These really are different maps,
but they look almost identical.
And the correlation is plain to see.
When Katrina struck, its powerful winds rapidly
shoved water from the Gulf of Mexico
into Lake Ponter train and overflowed it.
The levees that were designed to contain it
were not built up to standards high enough
to overcome this, and many failed.
As a result, the water spilled into the bowl
that is New Orleans, and the city was devastated.
Over 1800 lives were lost.
Over $150,000,000,000 in damage was caused.
And because of the mass exodus of refugees
escaping all of the chaos, the city's population
was reduced by more than half of what
it had been before the year after Katrina.
In 2006, New Orleans had been reduced to
a mere shadow of its former self.
It was then only the 94th largest city
in America, and it was the lowest population
the city had ever had since the 1870s.
Over the years since, new Orleans has managed
to admirably rebuild, but her population has still,
to this day, not ever managed to recover
beyond her pre Katrina 2005 population.
It was a catastrophic blow, but hurricanes and
the lake are but one of the many
problems that the city is facing.
The next is the Mississippi river itself.
Over thousands of years, the Mississippi's path has
constantly wandered across the landscape of Louisiana.
The Mississippi as we know it today has
basically only existed since the middle ages.
And when the French settled the city in the
18th century, they weren't exactly aware of that.
Beginning around 1900, the Mississippi's natural
wandering course began to change again.
Had it been left to its own devices, without any
human intervention, the Mississippi would have by now shifted its
primary path over here to the Acapula River.
And what remained of the river through New
Orleans would have effectively just become a stream.
In comparison, this would have destroyed New Orleans drinking
water supply and rendered her strategic location at the
mouth of the Mississippi pretty much obsolete.
So rationalizing that it would have been pretty
expensive to pretty much abandon the city and
push everybody over to the Acapula river.
Engineers decided instead to construct a massive series
of river control structures further up the river
to guarantee that the water would continue flowing
into the Mississippi as we know it today.
However, some geologists believe that if a future flood
is catastrophic enough, the system could be overwhelmed and
the Mississippi will find its way over to the
ace oflia and around New Orleans anyway.
And the Mississippi poses much more threats to
New Orleans than simply diverting itself around it.
Like lake ponter train, the Mississippi also likes
to flood a lot and is higher up
than a significant amount of New Orleans.
So artificial levees were constructed along its
banks to try and contain it.
However, this also had a
lot of unintended consequences.
Chief among them was the
destruction of Louisiana's coastline.
You see, the Mississippi River is chock full of sediment,
which is why the river always looks so brown.
But over thousands of years, the river continuously deposited
these sediments into the Gulf of Mexico and compounding
over time, creating newer and newer marshlands.
Immediately before the European discovery of
America, this is roughly what the
Louisiana coastline naturally looked like.
But after New Orleans was established and the
levees were constructed along the river's banks throughout
the 19th century, the sedimentrich water could no
longer reach and replenish any of these wetlands.
And when combined with rising sea levels in a myriad
of other manmade causes, they began to rapidly shrink.
In the past hundred years alone, louisiana has
lost thousands of square miles to the ocean.
And it's getting even worse all the time.
Since New Orleans itself is sinking by about 5 year and
sea levels are rising by about 3.6 to 4 year, the
water is creeping faster and closer to the New Orleans Bowl
all the time over the next 30 years.
By 2050, louisiana is projected to lose about
another 5800 wetlands, and the ocean itself will
be pretty much on New Orleans'doorstep.
At this point, New Orleans will be even
more surrounded by water than she is today
on all sides, which will only increase the
odds of catastrophic floods in the future.
Historically, Louisiana's wetlands have provided some kind
of barrier of defense between New Orleans
and hurricanes rampaging in from the Gulf.
But in the future, without them, new Orleans
will increasingly experience more and more direct impacts
from hurricanes that right now have an 11%
chance of hitting every single year.
But because of climate change, hurricanes
are happening more and more frequently.
So the odds of another big one hitting New
Orleans are only going up, while at the same
time, her defenses are growing weaker and weaker.
With geography abandoning her, New Orleans has been forced
to result more and more to higher numbers of
manmade defenses to overcome her now exposed and poor
location, like higher and stronger levees, floodgates pumping stations,
river controls, and dredging up new artificial land to
replace their natural wetland defenses.
But the really big problem that New Orleans is going to
have to overcome is that rising sea levels and flood risks
are not a unique problem faced by them alone.
But by dozens of other cities
across the United States as well. Such as New York.
Miami.
And others who.
Because they all have bigger populations and economies.
Will probably be priority targets for any
kind of federal flood protection funding.
So in the end, Louisiana itself is one of
the most impoverished states in the United States.
And without a lot of external federal funding, any manmade
structures they build still just might not end up being
enough compared with the overwhelming firepower that nature is bringing
to the table, say, for taking New Orleans and pushing
it somewhere else, like near the Acapellaa, where the Mississippi
is bound to probably just end up anyway sometime in
the next 1000 years.
I'm unsure of New Orleans'future and how
long the city has left, which is
a tragedy, because I love New Orleans.
But ultimately, in the end, there isn't any amount
of technology that can overcome the simple fact that
New Orleans is technically located within a bowl that's
surrounded by water, that's getting deeper and deeper and
even more surrounded by water with every passing hour.
New Orleans future is sadly not certain.
A couple weeks ago, Louisiana fell victim to its
second most destructive hurricane on record, behind Katrina.
While the total cost of the damage has
not yet been accurately calculated, it will certainly
be an excess of $50 billion.
The storm's devastation left over a million
people across Louisiana without power and brought
widespread flooding throughout the state.
And yet the levees of New Orleans held firm.
In their defense, a lot of what's happening today
is based on what happened yesterday, last week, last
year, or even last decade and beyond.
Anna's somebody with a lot of family around the Gulf
Coast and New Orleans, and as someone with knowledge of
New Orleans history and geography, the events of Hurricane IDA
had me worried and concerned for days.
But information on what exactly was happening was hard
to come by in the storm's immediate aftermath.
I wanted to understand what was happening in New
Orleans, a city that's dear to my heart but
not a place I currently live in.
And so I began keeping up with the
events by reading the frequent short articles that
were being posted to Morning Brew every morning.
This is what I love the most about using Morning Brew.
They're free daily newsletter gets you up to speed
on all the current events and news that you
need to know in business, finance and tech in
only five minutes, and in a way that's more
relevant, informative and frankly, witty than traditional news.
For example, while I was writing the script that
relied upon many of the Hurricane IDA articles for
context, I also got to read about El Salvador
adopting bitcoin as an official currency, how September 11
transformed the American defense industry, and why aluminum prices
hit their highest levels in ten years, all because
of a coup and guinea.
Since you watch reallife lore, I know that
you like getting a bit smarter and staying
better informed, and regular repeatable patterns of learning
are exactly the best way to do that.
So go ahead and start your mornings with Morning
Brew by subscribing completely for free when you click
the button that's on your screen right now or
by following the link that's down in the description.
It's one of the best ways that you can help support
this channel for free, and you get to stay up to
date with current events and be a better informed person.
It's seriously a win win.
And as always, thank you so much for watching.