This is the Sabachi City, an infrastructure project with a
very unusual approach because in this city, pretty much every
resident has their own private beach access on a lagoon
that leads directly into into the sea.
But constructing such a city means
overcoming tremendous engineering problems as project
planners battle with forces of nature.
But why did they choose this
costly approach of making a city?
Kuwait in the late 1980s was faced with a problem.
There was a great need for luxurious
housing in the country, which had become
rich through the export of crude oil.
But the small nation lacked the
space to meet this demand.
The northern and southern ends of Great Coast are
just 105 miles apart, and by 1989, when the
plans for a new city began to take shape,
much of the coastal area was already built up.
The capital Kuwait City, with its adjacent outskirts and
industrial suburbs, already stretched all the way from the
Kuwait Bay to far south down the coast.
Building further inland in the desert is not
very desirable for a variety of reasons.
After all, there are no usable
resources here to supply cities.
The ground is unstable and hardly suitable for construction,
and above all, there is an extremely dry heat. Here.
Living along the coast is more desirable as
the sea breeze ensures a milder climate, with
temperature fluctuations between day and night being reduced.
The idea to fix this is simple.
Instead of building directly on the limited shoreline
and creating a few new beachfront properties, one
could instead take channels that run inland, sneaking
through an area in such a way that
there is far more water access.
If you pull both of these cords straight, you can
see just how massively the coast can be extended.
Using this method, two potential project sites were
considered for the construction of this new city.
One area adjacent to the Shuwayk district in
Kuwait City, and the other one Alkira, not
far from the Saudi Arabian border.
But just before the plans really could take shape,
the entire project had to be put on hold
as the nation found itself entangled in a conflict.
On 2 August 1990, Iraq began invading Korea.
With ground troops coming from the border as
well as helicopters and boats from the water.
The Iraqi forces were able to advance to
Kura City within just hours, where British citizens
in a room overlooking their embassy captured footage
of the moment these forces arrived.
What followed was a several month long Iraqi occupation of
Korea and the eventual Gulf War that ended with the
liberation of the country in late February 1991.
Even if the occupation was overcome, tremendous suffering
had happened and there was no money, time
or need for costly new construction projects.
The war also caused massive environmental damage,
from a huge oil spill to longlasting
fires clouding the country for months.
It ended up taking another six years until
the plants for the Sea City were resumed.
And as environmentally destructive as the past phase
was for the country, this project should now
focus on dealing well with the environment.
The developers chose the area in Alkhiran and decided on an
approach in which the exact form of the project is strongly
guided by the natural forces of sea and wind.
The project's site was characterized by two
existing tidal creeks, with water levels rising
and falling with the tides.
And aside from the Alkyron resort, a popular recreational
destination, this piece of land had not been developed
based on the natural currents of these tidal creeks.
A master plan was drafted to create a
complex channel system with two additional C entrances.
But as simple as this approach seems,
a number of difficulties quickly became apparent.
One of them is that the water
quality could easily become poor due to
the lack of circulation in these channels.
If the water is not regularly exchanged, this
promotes algae growth, and the channels could become
foulsmelling salt ponds unattractive for residents.
At the same time, the water flow flushing
these channels should also not be too fast,
because residents are supposed to swim here comfortably.
And how can you be sure that these geometrically
shaped canals designed on plan will not be deformed
over the years by the powerful natural forces of
the water threatening residential buildings with flooding?
In order to prevent these issues, planners developed
a complex computer model simulating the natural currents.
Extensive data was collected at the project site
about wind speeds and directions and ocean currents.
With this data, a schematic computer model
could be created which simulates the hydrodynamic
properties of the entire system.
This way, additional connecting channels were introduced in areas
where the simulation showed that the water flow was
too fast, because if you introduce another channel, the
water has more space to go, the flow slows
down, and as a side effect, the risk of
coastal erosion is also reduced.
But even though the adjustments based on the
computer model promised improvement, it still appeared that
the water exchange was too irregular in certain
areas, which would result in bad water quality.
One possibility to fix this would be by
simply pumping the water out from these areas.
But pumping stations require a lot
of energy and are expensive also.
Such a solution means pumping will be required
indefinitely, so it's less of a solution to
the problem than an elaborate workaround.
Therefore, the engineers came up with another
idea that would allow the lagoons to
be completely flushed only by natural forces.
They achieved this by strategically
placing socalled tidal gates.
These gates are opened up at high tide simply
due to the water pressure pushing them open.
However, at low tides, with the water
flowing the opposite direction, the water pushes
these gates to a closed position.
This way, the system is completely self regulating.
And the computer simulation shows how
the flushing of fresh water can
be significantly improved using these gates.
While the project was finally beginning to take
shape in the early two thousand s, with
excavators digging the first canals and the flooding
of the first section with water.
Starting in 2004, another project, also
in the Persian Gulf, suddenly attracted
lots of attention around the world.
The huge land reclamation projects of Dubai, most
notably Palm Jamera, began to take shape.
What was done in Dubai is
a very different approach to essentially
the same problem creating additional coastline.
While in Kuwait, channels were dug into the
barren desert in Dubai, sand was dredged from
the sea floor to create artificial new islands.
There are major differences between these
two approaches, especially when it comes
to the effect on the environment.
While in Kuwait, the already existing natural currents and
tidal creeks informed the shape of the design.
In Dubai, the form of the islands was playfully chosen to
resemble the shapes of palm trees or of a world map.
And constructing such a land reclamation
project involves a difficulttosolve contradiction.
On one hand, the Manmade Islands must be
protected from the forces of the ocean currents,
which is done with rigid breakwater rinks.
It's necessary because in the long run, these
islands are not stable by themselves, as the
shape of coastal land is not formed by
chance, but results from complex natural forces, oftentimes
continuously evolving coastal landscapes over the years.
The contradiction is that by building
such protective breakwater rinks, this also
prevents the regular water exchange.
For example, while the more exposed islands in
Dubai's, the world project struggle with coastal erosion,
the palm Jumera, which is better protected by
the extensive breakwater, struggles with water quality problems
as the water in the inner part of
the palm is almost stagnant.
In Kuwait's Sea City, on the other hand, the
beaches located near the sea entrance were set up
with clearance so that they can be shaped naturally,
while the canals inside the land are not subjected
to the strong ocean forces.
It turns out that dealing harmoniously with nature
was a major focus at Kuwait's Sea City.
While the dredging and creation of land
reclamation represents a harsh encroachment on the
speciesrich marine habitat, the digging of new
channels in Karait's arid desert actually creates
new additional habitats for marine life.
The stony breakwater in Sea City was only filled
with mortar above the waterline, leaving open underwater spaces
which offer ideal habitats for marine life.
In addition, mangroves and other plants that can
grow in dry conditions were planted on specifically
created islands in order to structurally strengthen the
marine bay and create natural habitats.
Instead of bringing the desert into the sea, krait
Sea City brings the sea into the desert.
Still, the transformation of such a large area
was an enormous challenge, and it is intrusive.
Countless hours of dredging were required to
remove material to build the canals.
With the project growing over the years and
new sections being opened regularly, the planners hope
to eventually house 2500 people in this city. Today.
Along the canals, you mostly find residential
villas, high income apartments, as well as
some hotel resorts and several marinas.
While many plots also remain undeveloped, if one understands
the word city to mean a diverse coexistence of
living spaces, office space, cultural institutions, as well as
public space, this city is not that.
It is a car dependent development that focuses entirely
on private living space with direct beach access.
While they have transformed this area and literally
move mountains to achieve this, it appears that
other aspects of modern city planning have been
much less of a priority.
And despite the project being constructed in Kuwait,
a country which owes its economic prosperity to
the trade with petroleum products, there has been
a strong focus on environmental solutions.
Notable also considering that the construction of
this project had to be put on
hold during the Gulf War that stood
out for its unprecedented catastrophic environmental impact.
When.
Instead of digging artificial canals.
Kuwait had to spend about one 5 billion U. S.
Dollars just to extinguish fires all across the
country as Iraqi soldiers withdrawing from the land
in the final stages of the war had
set countless oil wells on fire.
An act of sabotage with farreaching consequences.
Because once such a fire has been set.
It was almost impossible to extinguish it.
If I were to make an indepth video on
YouTube about the Gulf War and the oil fires,
there's no way it's ever going to be monetised
and you probably would never see it. Still.
I have made a fulllength companion video explaining the
full story of the oil field fires with incredible
archival footage from the time it has become a
video I'm very proud of and which I have
just uploaded to Nebula today.
Where you can see it
alongside my other exclusive videos.
Such as a 3D animated short film
I produced about the global refugee crisis.
Or a full length video about the investigation
into the crash of flight MH 17.
And besides me, there is original content
from lots of amazing educational creators.
The best way to get all this amazing content
is definitely with the CuriosityStream Nebula bundle deal, which
at current sales price is less than $15 a
year to get full access to both sides.
And CuriosityStream has absolutely incredible documentaries such as
Dubai's Vertical City, which covers the life inside
Burj Khalifa, the highest building on Earth.
So not only do you get access to two full
fledged streaming sites, you also will support a variety of
independent educational creators and enable me to make these extra
videos that just can't work on YouTube.
So please make sure to do so by clicking
this button on screen right now, or by following
the link that's below in the description.
Thank you so much for watching.