In 2001, the United States military invaded Afghanistan
20 years later, the U-S is withdrawing
and the Taliban appears to be stronger than ever, with control of up to 85 % of the country
In 1979, the Soviet Union also invaded Afghanistan
and after nine years, they also withdrew The regime they fought so hard to prop up
almost immediately collapsed
And before them
the British Empire invaded Afghanistan on three separate occasions and failed to conquer them in each instance
Today, afghanistan has a smaller population than California
in a territory that's only a little larger than France
So how is it that a country of this small size was capable of resisting three of the world's most powerful military juggernauts from history
There's a lot of answers to that question
but let's start with the easiest to understand
and perhaps the most obvious geography
In reality, afghanistan is little more than a geographical expression
All of her borders were arbitrarily drawn up by outside foreign powers more than a century ago
Its small population is composed of a loose association of 14 different ethno linguistic groups and numerous more tribes
many of which
like the Uzbeks to g Greeks and Pashtons, straddle the country's borders
artificial boundaries set up by Westerners hundreds of years ago that mean very little to them
The Peshtons make up nearly half of afghanistan's population a day
but two thirds of all Pashtons live next door in neighboring Pakistan
and are a minority group there
The border between Afghanistan and Pakistan runs directly through the Pashton tribal area and divides the 60 million Pashton people between both countries
This boundary was artificially dissent by the British Empire back in 1893
and to date, not a single government based in Afghanistan has ever officially ratified it
Imagine if in Europe, poland was divided between Germany and Russia
and a wall was built directly between both sides of where the Poles live
Obviously
the Poles would never recognize this border and routinely cross it visit family and friends
And the pastones largely treat the Afghan Pakistan border the very same way
The border here is extremely mountainous and rural
so patrolling it from the Pakistani government's perspective has always been quite challenging
This has allowed pastun insurgents operating with an Afghanistan the valuable ability to easily escape across the border into the friendly pastun areas of Pakistan
regroup and recover, recruit more men and then travel back into Afghanistan
freshly supplied and ready for more combat
Neither the Afghan border nor the Taliban recognize this border as legitimate
and there are at least 235 known crossing points across the border and through the mountains between both countries
Militants, drugs, money and supplies can easily be smuggled into Afghanistan by way of Pakistan
And it's made all the easier by many of the pastones of Pakistan being more sympathetic to the Afghan or Taliban cause
This has led many people to label the Afghan Pakistan border as the most dangerous border in the entire world
And recently, as a result of all of this, by the end of June
pakistan has finally finished building a fence across the entire length of the border
specifically to stop all of this
and has restricted border crossings to only legally designated locations
But this is all only the start of what makes Afghanistan an almost most impossible place to conquer
I mean, just look at the map
Afghanistan is a landlocked so getting your troops and supplies there requires the cooperation of at least one of the six countries that borders it
iran, turkmenistan, uzbekistan, tajikistan, china and of course, pakistan
But even once you get across one of the countries and you arrive at afghanistan's borders
you're going to be met with afghanistan's mon you mentally challenging terrain
Despite being in the center of the world's most populous continent
afghanistan has always been heavily isolated and largely rural and underpopulated
Because of this
the high peaks of the Hindu kush Mountain range was some of the tallest and biggest mountains found anywhere on the planet
75 % of Afghanistan territories consider to be mountainous
and nearly half of our territory has an elevation above 2000 m
which makes Afghanistan among the most mountainous countries of the world
and among the most isolated too
As a result, these huge mountains act like natural walls in more ways than one
They help to keep invaders out
but they also separate communities within and make transporting supplies across challenging
These are all very difficult factors to overcome from the perspective of any outside invader
There are dozens of valleys that zigzag in between the mountains of Afghanistan
where most of the population resides
and since they're surrounded by some of the biggest and most formidable mountains on Earth
it's always been difficult to travel between them
And consequently, they're each sort of their own little world in sight of Afghanistan
Over thousands of years, each ended up developing their own rather distinctive cultures
identities, beliefs, tribes and rulers
and thus there's very little sense of Afghan nationhood
And Afghan patriotism has never been a particularly strong motivating factor because of all these separate and rural communities that are difficult to travel between
The grip of any government has always been weak and intermittent
while the valleys have largely governed themselves autonomously, especially in the countryside
Any semblance of Afghan national unity has always been a direct consequence of foreign powers invading and attempting to impose their rule over the whole
Like with the British Soviets in recently, americans, historically, end up to the present day
To an extent
afghanistan continues to operate in a way that's more similar to the Holy Roman Empire than the European Union
The ruler in the capital city, kabul may nominally wheel desure authority over the entire realm
like the Holy Roman emperor
but is not able to wheel defecto authority over all of the various princes
valleys, tribes and clans
Just like the Holy Roman
any invader coming into occupy Afghanistan will struggle with all of the same issues that a domestic ruler
Well, afghanistans Geography is not very conducive to a centralized authority
and neither is afghanistan's infrastructure
Enforcing your authority across the various Afghan valleys means that you must move your troops and supplies from one to another through the various mountain passes that are often narrow and incredibly easy positions to set up an ambush in as a defender
These passes basically act like natural choke points for the movement of people all across Afghanistan
And up until the 1960s, there were hardly even any roads to speak of that went through them
Control over just a few of these mountain passes can ensure control over an entire valley
and sabotaging one can block the flow of supplies and troops for days
weeks or even longer, depending upon the severity of the damage
Soviets invaded the country
the Mujahadin defenders would ambush Soviet convoys as they traveled through these passes
and then immediately flee back and vanish into the caves of the mountains
When they were fired back upon, they would set up road blocks at river crossings or in other passes
and in some instances, were successful enough to block entire roads for months or even years
The town of Coast
near the Pakistan border was permanently sealed off from the rest of the country for the entire war by the muj Adine
sabotaging a series of strategic roads
and the government forces blocked inside could only be supplied by air
And when the Americans invaded, these passes were just as vital
so significant for them was the Cyber pass here
the easiest and most direct path through the Hindu cush between the Indian subcontinent and Central Asia
This path has been used for thousands of years by conquerors, traders and missionaries all alike
and is without a doubt one of the most strategic locations to hold on the entire planet
At one point
nearly 80 % of all NATO and U-S supplies that were being brought into Afghanistan by road
We're all coming through the Cyber Pass via Pakistan
which is kind of ironic
because most of the Taliban s equipment were also coming from across the border in Pakistan
just at different and more rural crossing point
The Taliban knew how critically important the Kyber Pass was to the American war effort
so it was a frequent target of sabotage efforts
In 2009, the Taliban blew up a bridge here, the temporarily shut down the entire pass
and America was forced to broaden their supply lines into Afghanistan through the three central Asian bordering countries as well
In the years before all of this war
the Afghan government had attempted a build of circular highway that would connect all of their major economic centers together
But over the decades of civil war and Soviet intervention, the highway was in very bad shape
By the time the United States invaded in 2001
there were only a mere 50 km of paved roads to speak of in the entire country
That's bigger than France
For comparison
france has million kilometers of paved roads in a smaller and significantly less mountainous territory
The lack of good roads only made the disparate valleys and communities of the Afghan interior even more isolated from each other
and may transporting troops and supplies a logistical nightmare for the Americans and the Soviets before them
none of which helped at all for the countrys stability
As with all things in Afghanistan
the development of new roads is difficult and expensive because of the harsh
mountainous terrain
the cold winter weather that often choose roads up and sabotage from the Taliban and other insurgents
Building a repairing roads in the country necessitates hiring security and necessitates building them across harsh geography and climates
which means that it can get incredibly expensive, as much as $5 million per mile in some locations
And this is all in a country where the average person only makes a little over over $500 a year
one of the poorest and least developed nations on the planet
The construction of a single mile of road within Afghanistan is about the combined annual wages of 90 800 Afghanis
So obviously the funding for all of these projects has to come from abroad
Ultimately, afghanistan is easy to invade and take over
but it's almost impossible to effectively hold it for long
The landscape is huge, with a lot of rural and empty places for insurgents and rebels to hide
Getting troops in and establishing supply lines through massive mountains and narrow passes is challenging
An easy for guerrilla combatants to harass and disrupt
The relationship with neighboring Pakistan is complex
and peshton insurgents can easily cross the border, regroup without much fear
and then return to fight in Afghanistan whenever ready
The flow of insurgent supplies
money and manpower across the border is difficult to stop through the hundreds of high and remote mountain passes
and requires the cooperation of Pakistan
which she is sometimes willing to give
and other times not
Centralized rule is almost impossible to enforce outside of Kabul
by way of afghanistan's geographic reality
And a nation building is inherently impossible, because even the concept of an Afghan nation
among afghanistan's various ethnicities and tribes, is tenuous at best
and certainly radically different from the Western idea of nation state such as Germany or France
The colonial era borders of Afghanistan, dictated by the British over a century ago
are probably the biggest core reason for afghanistan's instability
But Afghanistan has been particularly unstable, even by former British colonial medaling standards
For the past 43 years, afghanistan, pakistan, has been embroiled in constant warfare
and it's an incredibly complex story to tell
From a communist revolution that enforced state atheism in one of the most conservative and religious countries on the planet to an invasion and occupation by the Soviet Union
three subsequent civil wars
and then the invasion of the American Africans and NATO and the United States occupation
That's all set to finally end after nearly 20 years, in about a month from now
It is one of the most fascinating
violent and controversial conflicts of both the 20th and 21st centuries
and unfortunately not acceptable for me to cover on Youtube due to their terms of service
I know how making videos on Youtube works
and I know that this video already has a super high chance of being demonitized and unpromoted by youtube's algorithm because of what I'm discussing
But the moment that I really start diving into the whole history of the Afghan conflicts
why they began, how they were fought
and how it all led to where we are today
It's a guarantee that this video will be censored
and you won't get to see it
So instead
I created another full length companion video to this one with all of that controversial but fascinating information included
and uploaded that version to Nebula, which, as you've probably heard by now
is home to tons of exclusive, ad free content, like my entire modern conflict series
with additional full length videos you can go watch right now
detailing the Israel Palestine conflicts, the 2020 Armenia Azerbaijan war
and the ongoing russo Ukraine war in the don Bass
Of course
the reason why all of these videos are only on Nebula is because the youtube algorithm actually punishes me and all other creators forever trying anything new
But Nebula is a different platform without an algorithm and without ads
It's just a platform about great and unique content made by great and independent educational creators
Nebula's ecosystem enables us to take big risks with expensive projects like america's big ghost Town
My own 35 minute long documentary shot on location around the Sultan Sea
the largest lake in California
and arguably america's greatest environmental disaster
that drove thousands from their homes
and as a result, created america's largest ghost town
and plenty of other projects for more creators you probably know
like whenover productions half as interesting, tom Scott and many others
The best way to get access to Nebula and all of this incredible content is definitely through the amazing Curiosity Stream
Nebula bundle deal
With its current sales price, it's less than $15 a year to get access to both sites
And curiositys Stream has some phenomenal stuff too, like Afghanistan 1979, a 57 minute long
fantastic documentary that dives deep into the entire course of the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan and the subsequent war in amazing detail
If you felt like my video didn't go into and this is the video for you
And it includes actual interviews with surviving veterans of the war from both the Afghan and Soviet perspectives alike
including Mikhail Gorbachev, with enormous amounts of historical footage and context
I really can't recommend this documentary enough
and I genuinely don't know about a better deal to exist in streaming
You get to streaming sites
both with content you'll actually watch and all for less than $15 a year at the current sales price
But what's more
signing up will actually help countless independent educational creators beyond just real Life lower
So please make sure to do so by clicking this button here on screen right now
which will take you directly to the curiosity stream com, such real life Law
where you can sign up for less than $15 a year for both services
or by following the link down below in the description
And is always Thank you so much for watching
I'm going to