in the early
2000s, real estate developers saw an enormous opportunity in
creating artificial land off the coast of dubai
the real estate
boom in the emirate seemed unstoppable, and the demand for ocean properties was huge
dubai had already expanded along most of its coast
soon, the keel properties, a real estate company
owned by the government of dubai, made plans to radically change the region
all within just two decades, the company plant freed different island projects that, when viewed from space, should represent the shape of palm trees, palmjamira, palm, jabil elise and lastly, palmdera, by far the largest one in addition, the world, was announced
different areas were plant, from low density housing, high density complexes and islands that can be used commercially
in a 2nd phase, the world was planned to be supplemented by a never even bigger project the universe
man made islands were planned that resembled the shape of the sun, the moon, as well as the planets of the solar system, the milky way, and a distant galaxy next to palm jabo elise
another gigantic project was to be created the dubai waterfront
these islands should be formed like a star in crescent, an important symbol in islam
and the construction project was advertised as the largest man made development project worldwide
the shape should also serve as a shelter to protect palm jabo elise from erosion
with all of these projects, most of the coast of dubai would have been transformed, as on one side, the emirate of abu dhabi begins, and on the other side there is the emirate of shajah
in retrospect, the level of confidence with which these projects were advanced is astonishing
but the islands were seen as prestige projects that served a larger goal of developing dubai into a major tourist hotspot, and thereby creating new income sources for a place that gained most of its wealth for the extraction of oil
now let's take a look at what happened to these ambitious plans
in 2001, nickele property started building the palmjamara
this project alone would double the length of the coastline of dubai
in 2006, the land reclamation was completed, and the 1st apartments were already handed over
the strands of the palm mainly host private houses, while a number of larger luxury hotels were built on the breakwater ring around the palm that protects the palm from storms
while palm jamaro was still under construction, over projects started to take shape
the st century seemed to have reached a new peak in the rate of growth of dubai
the real estate market experienced a rapid boom, and a number of prestige projects, such as the bourge califa, the largest building in the world, were built
in september 2008, the atlantis hotel on palmjamira celebrated its opening with a firework show on the entire palm
but the celebrations couldn't change that
the international financial crisis started to affect dubai
just last week, dubai spent $20 million for a party to open the atlanta hotel
the headline was, dubai parties. as the rest of the world reels from the economic crisis, perhaps not anymore
dubai has been hit by the global financial crisis, especially in real estate
mega projects like the artificial island off the coast are in danger of collapse
many construction sites have shut down due to a declining demand
the price of plots of land fell rapidly
in a development of palm, jabo elise came to a standstill in 2011
the keel properties offered investors refunds, and a project has been done hold ever since
the empty sand banks that reach 7 km, or 4.3 mi, into the sea appear strangely forgotten
the palm is located behind the jebel elise port, with no city development near it, and most of the visions dreamed up by the project planners seemingly evaporated in a pluff of sand
the land reclamation of the dubai waterfront is nowhere near as advanced, but you can already see the shape of some of the islands on satellite images
this project as well, has been discontinued
a similar situation exists with palmdera
the land reclamation had already progressed, but it is far from complete
in 2014, the keel decided to try to save this project by rebranding it
instead of continuing to create new land, the project was scaled down and is now just called darra islands, and there is current construction work underway with a plan mall to high rise buildings in a shopping street
finally, the world the land creation was mostly completed, and a large part of the islands had already been sold before the financial crisis, but the islands were just not developed further, as many of the investors that bought them were facing their own problems in the aftermath of the financial crisis
and although investments into new projects in dubai increased after the crisis, the world project couldn't benefit from this, as there was less confidence on the return on any such investments
ten years after the initial project reveal, the world already seemed to no longer fit
in the current time, many concerns about the longevity of the project arose, as news reports stated that the smaller channels between the islands started to send up, and the rising sea levels are growing danger for project like this
in general, growing concerns around land reclamation projects came up
residents at palmjamera criticized their water quality
while the breakwater is necessary to protect the palm from erosion, it also hinders the natural tidal movement, and seawater within the palm became stagnant
additionally, environmental concerns got more attention, piling up hundreds of thousands of tons of sand on a seabed that previously had been almost evenly flat
has an impact on marine ecology
the islands are composed mainly of sand that was stretched from dubai's shallow coastal waters, and there are concerns that this leads to a destabilization of the coastal soil, which could lead to an erosion of the natural coastline
even if these consequences have been known for a long time, it is becoming increasingly difficult to market projects that are considered environmentally harmful
many of the projects promoted in recent years are therefore trying to incorporate environmental compatibility
in addition, the difficult living conditions of migrant construction workers in dubai, is a topic that is receiving more media attention
nevertheless, there are development projects on these islands that are starting to take shape
initially, there was only one island that had been developed
the villa served as a showhouse to promote the project
in summer 2012, the royal island beach club opened on lebanon island
the club hosts daytime tourists that can get there by boat
the biggest project, however, was announced in 2014
an austrian real estate investor plans to develop a number of projects on the european islands
the project is called the heart of europe, and the goal is to create kind of a mini version of europe, with luxurious hotels that are inspired by places like venice or monaco, in addition to a number of restaurants with european food, the investor also plans to build a plaza on the swiss island, where there will be artificial snow, the project is currently under construction, and time will tell whether it will bring the desired economic success
there are risky development projects almost everywhere in the world, and everywhere in the world
some of them fail. in urban development, prestige projects often serve a greater world than being financially successful by their own as they can attract tourists to a region and therefore support the greater local economy in a variety of ways
in addition to attracting tourism, such prestige projects also often serve as national pride, or they intend to symbolize the start of a new era, e.g
by using new construction methods or by breaking world records
if to bias question for creating planned landmarks, then the same criticism must certainly be applied elsewhere as well
but still, the question remains how these projects that change the coastal landscape of dubai will be viewed in retrospect at a time when dub ice growth slows down, and when the ambitious dream that this city represents stops being built and just has to be lived
thank you so much for watching
i recently received a package from youtube with the silver creator award, and so i just wanted to use that as an opportunity to say thank you
there are many more videos in production, so if you enjoy this content, please join in and subscribe
singer