This is the United States
This is Louisiana
and this is New Orleans
And without constant human intervention, this city literally wouldn't exist
It has perhaps the worst geographic location of any major city in America
and there are countless reasons why that are all named water
New Orleans, the city that is almost completely surrounded by water on all sides
To the north is Lake Poncho Train
In the center is the Mississippi River
Into the south and east is the ever encroaching seawater from the Gulf of Mexico
To make matters even worse
65 % of the New Orleans metropolitan area is located either ats or far beneath sea level
a greater percentage than even the Netherlands
which is only about a 3rd beneath sea level
This means that when you take a look in New Orleans from the side
it's effectively just a big bowl that's surrounded on nearly all of its edges by water
And whenever the water tips over the sides from either the river or the lake, the city drown
And to make matters even more severe
new Orleans is placement directly at the Gulf of mexico's edge makes it the most frequent target of hurricanes in America
with an 11 % risk of being slammed by one every single year
Hurricanes make the flooding problem in the city even worse
But that's still not all due to a variety media reasons that I'll get into later in the video
Louisiana's coastline has been losing the war against the water for the greater part of a century
Now, over the past hundred years, 2000 sq mi
Of land has been conquered by the ocean in Louisiana, south that's twice the size of Luxemberg
And the ocean's advances are accelerating to the tune of about one football field worth of land every hour
24 h a day, 365 days a year
This is putting the ocean and its waters dangerously closer and closer to New Orleans every single hour
And it's placing the city on a time bomb
Southern Louisiana is slowly drowning
And it ultimately begs the question
since nature seems to think that settling a city here was such an obviously terrible idea
then why didn't humans
The answer to that is because, of course
it never really seemed like a bad location until fairly recently
In fact, for most of Americas and even humanity's history
the area around New Orleans was without a doubt one of the most important locations on the entire planet to control
Take a look at the map of the world
Pretend that you've just begun a game of civilization, where you're low in the tech tree
and look at where the best locations to build a wealth city are going to be on the North American continent
I would argue
for the area around New Orleans being historically the number one pick for one incredibly important reason
Despite all the risks of flooding and natural disasters
new Orleans sits near the mouth of the Mississippi River
and by setting up a choke point here
one can fully control all of the trade in transportation flowing into and out of it
This is vital, because by entering the Mississippi here
you can travel throughout almost the entirety of the North American interior by way of the Mississippi River Basin
Every single one of these creeks streams, rivers
eventually all flow into the Mississippi and find their way down to New Orleans and the Ocean
Until the advent of modern technology, like railroads, planes or highways
it was rivers and waterways all across the world which served as humanity's high speed transportation and trade arteries
And the Mississippi is the biggest and the most important system of them all
anywhere on the planet
In fact
the Greater Mississippi River Basin has more kilometers of navigable internal waterways than the entire rest of the world all combined
Has This fact is enormous because it was basically the world's largest natural transportation system on any continent
That today flows through 31 U-S states and two Canadian provinces
This system literally connected almost the entire North American continental mainland to the Atlantic Ocean and the rest of the world from there
And all of it could effectively be dominated by whoever controlled just this small show point right near the entrance to the Mississippi River
The French were the 1st big empire who recognized this area's immense strategic value
and a little over 300 years ago
they founded the small settlement of New Orleans here along the Rivers Curve
where it created a natural levy about one and a half meters above sea level
comparatively higher than the surrounding swamplands that were beneath sea level
The initial small settlement fared well against floods and hurricanes
and a century later
found itself under the possession of a new and future global empire the United States
The Mississippi River and all of its various tributary stretching as far as Denver
minneapolis to Moine Omaha
kansas City in Oklahoma City
enabled millions of American settlers to venture out and conquer the West
And they could reach all of these places via New Orleans
and all of the goods they would end up producing would flow back to New Orleans
As America expanded westwards
the Mississippi River became roughly the device line between East and west within the continental States
and the importance of New Orleans became ever more apparen't
If any enemy power were to gain control of it
they could shut the entire river down and effectively cut America in half and block all of the massive volume of trade flowing down it from the dozens of other states that were making new from New Orleans one of the wealthiest cities in the world
In fact, by the 1840s, new Orleans was america's 3rd biggest city
behind only New York in Baltimore
And by the time of the Civil War, it was easily the south's largest and most important city
River Boats and barges easily transported luxury goods like cotton from southern states like Mississippi
and industrial goods from northern factories up in Illinois, indiana and Ohio
And New Orleans was at the zenith of her power and influence
But after the Civil War, the city's fortunes were dramatically reverse
The invention of new technologies like the railroad introduced new transportation and trade routes that largely bypass New orleans' location down in the southeast
As more and more railroads
and later interstate highways for trucks and cars and airports for planes were built
the crucial importance of the Mississippi and its various riverways diminished by the 20th century
The Mississippi no longer had a monopoly on Middle america's transportation and trade
and in New orleans's monopoly over a minutes to that system no longer mattered quite as much
By World War Two, new Orleans had plummeted from america's 3rd largest city to only her 15th
and despite reaching the height of her popular in 1960 with about 620000 people
she was no longer even the biggest city in the American South
with cities like Dallas and Houston having passed her up with their much more rapid growth
Thereafter, new Orleans would enter into a slow and steady decline with economic opportunity
Moving on to other parts of the country, new Orleans lost 18 % of her population in only 30 years
Between 19 72000
Faced with a serious demographic crisis like this
the leaders of the city at the time decided that they needed to encourage more growth by developing more land
But the problem with that is that New Orleans was founded as an 18th century outpost
and its expansion from those borders into a modern
sprawling city was always doomed to be severely limited by simple geography
As New Orleans developed around her colonial era core that was on some of the highest ground available in the area
she had no other choice but to expand further into the swampy and flood prone lands that were closer to in eventually even beneath sea level
which was a dangerous decision
In order to develop the swamp land even further, the city began draining out all of the water
which caused the soil beneath to compact and led to the modern city above sinking
Today, parts of New Orleans are sinking by as much as 5 cm a year
And when you remember that most of the city is already beneath sea level and right next to several major bodies of water
you can understand why this is all catastrophically dangerous
What makes matters even worse is the fact that sea levels are only rising as time goes on
which is making the bowl shape of New Orleans, surrounded by precarious water on all sides
more and more dangerous as the st century continues
With all of that in mind, let's analyze all of New orleans' contemporary geographic issues
1st Up Lake Ponter Train
I want you to look at this map of the elevation levels throughout New Orleans
And now I want you to look at this map that shows the areas with the most severe flooding from Hurricane Katrina in 2005
These really are different maps
but they look almost identical
and the correlation is plain to see
When Katrina struck its powerful winds
rapidly shoved water from the Gulf of Mexico into Lake Poncho Train and overflowed it
The levies that were designed to contain it were not built up to standards high enough to overcome this
and many failed
As a result, the water spilled into the bowl that is New Orleans
and the city was devastated
Over 18 hundred lives were lost
Over a hundred and $50 billion in damage was caused
And because of the mass exodus of refugees escaping all of the chaos
the city's population was reduced by more than half of what it had been before
The year after Katrina in 2006, new Orleans had been reduced to a mere shadow of its former self
It was then only the 94th largest city in America
and it was the lowest population the city had ever had since the 18 seventys
Over the years since, new Orleans has managed to admirably rebuild
but her population has still, to this day
not ever managed to recover beyond her pre Katrina 2005 population
It was a catastrophic blow
but hurricanes in the lake are but one of the the many problems that the city is facing
The next is the Mississippi River itself
Over thousands of years
the mississippi's path has constantly wandered across the landscape of Louisiana
The Mississippi as we know it today has basically only existed since the Middle Ages
and when the French settled the city in the 18th century, they weren't exactly aware of that
Beginning around 1900, the mississippi's natural wandering course began to change again
Had it been left to its own devices, without any human intervention
the Mississippi would have by now shifted its primary path over here to the Achafalia River
and what remained of the river through New Orleans would have effectively just become a stream
In comparison
this would have destroyed New orleans's drinking water supply and rendered her strategic location at the mouth of the Mississippi pretty much obsolete
So rationalizing that it would have been pretty expensive to pretty much abandon the city and push everybody over to the Asha Feli
The river engineers decided instead to construct a massive series of river control structures further up the river to guarantee that the water would continue flowing into the Mississippi as we know it today
However, some geologists believe that if a future flood is catastrophic enough
the system could be overwhelmed
and the Mississippi will find its way over to the Feliah and around New Orleans anyway
And the Mississippi poses much more threats to New Orleans than simply diverting itself around it like Lake Poncho Train
The Mississippi also likes to flood a lot
and is higher up than a significant amount of New Orleans
so our official levies were constructed along its banks to try and contain it
However, this also had a lot of unintended consequences
Chief among them was the destruction of louisiana's coastline
You see that the Mississippi River is chalk full of sediment
which is why the river always looked so brown
But over thousands of years
the river continuously deposited these sediments into the Gulf of Mexico
and compounding over time, created newer and newer marshlands
Immediately before the European discovery of America
this is roughly what the Louisiana coast line naturally looked like
But after New Orleans was established and the levies were constructed along the rivers banks throughout the 19th century
the sediment rich water could no longer reach and replenish any of These are wetlands
and when combined with rising sea in a myriad of other man made causes
they began to rapidly shrink
In the past hundred years alone, louisiana has lost thousands of square miles to the ocean
and it's getting even worse all the time
Since New Orleans itself is sinking by about 5 cm a year
and sea levels are rising by about before millimeters a year
the water is creeping faster and closer to the New Orleans Bowl all the time
Over the next 30 years, by 2050
louisiana is projected to lose about another 50 800 km² of wetlands
and the ocean itself will be pretty much on New orleans' doorstep
At this point, new Orleans will be even more surrounded by water than she is today on all sides
which will only increase the odds of catastrophic floods in the future
Historically
louisiana's wetlands have provided some kind of barrier of defense between New Orleans and hurricanes rampaging in from the Gulf
But in the future, without
new Orleans will increasingly experience more and more direct impacts from hurricanes that right now have an percent chance of hitting every single year
But because of climate change, hurricanes are happening more and more frequently
so the odds of another big one hitting New Orleans are only going up
while at the same time
her defenses are growing weaker and weaker with geography abandoning her New Orleans has been forced to result more and more
to higher numbers of man made defenses to overcome her now exposed in poor location
like higher and stronger levies
floodgates, pumping stations
river controls and dredging up new artificial land to replace their natural wet defenses
But the really big problem that New Orleans is going to have to overcome is that rising sea levels and flood risks are not a unique problem faced by them alone
but by dozens of other cities across the United States as well
such as New York, miami and others, who
because they all have bigger populations and economies
will probably be priority targets for any kind of federal flood protection funding
So in the end, louisiana itself is one of the most impoverished states in the United States
and without a lot of external federal funding
any man made structures they build still just might not end up being enough compared with the overwhelming firepower than nature is bringing to the table
Say, for taking New Orleans and pushing it somewhere else, like near the Asha Fallaya
where the Mississippi is bound to probably just end up anyway, sometime in the next thousand years
I'm unsure of New orleans' future and how long the city has left
which is a tragedy, because I love New Orleans
But ultimately, in the end
there isn't any amount of technology that can overcome the simple fact that New Orleans is technically located within a bowl that's surrounded by water
that's getting deeper and deeper and even more surrounded by water with every passing hour
New orleans's future is sadly not certain
A couple weeks ago
louisiana fell victim to its 2nd most destructive hurricane on record, behind Katrina
While the total cost of the damage has not yet been accurately calculated
it will certainly be an excess of $50 billion
The storm's devastation left over a million people across Louisiana without power and brought widespread flooding throughout the state
And yet the levies of New Orleans held firm in their defense
A lot of what's happening today is based on what happened yesterday, last week, last year
or even last decade and beyond
With a lot of family around the Gulf Coast and New Orleans
and as someone with knowledge of New orleans' history and geography
the events of Hurricane Ida had me worried and concerned for days
But information on what exactly was happening was hard to come by
In the storms immediate aftermath, I wanted to understand what was happening in New Orleans
That's dear to my heart
but not a place I currently live in
And so I began keeping up with the events by reading the frequent short articles that were being posted to Morning Brew every morning
This is what I love the most about using Morning Brew
They're free daily newsletter gets you up to speed on all the current events and news that you need to know in business
finance and tech in only 5 min and in a way that's more relevant
informative, and, frankly, witty, than traditional news
E.g.
while I was writing the script that relied upon many of the Hurricane Ida articles for context
I also got to read about El Salvador adopting Bitcoin as an official currency
how september 11 transformed the American defense industry
and while aluminum prices hit their highest levels in ten years, all because of a coup in Guinea
Since you watch real life law
I know that you like getting a bit smarter and staying better informed
and regular, repeatable patterns of learning are exactly the best way to do that
So go ahead and start your mornings with Morning through by subscribing completely for free when you click the button that's on your screen right now
or by following the length that's down in the description
It's one of the best ways that you can help support this channel for free
and you get to stay up to date with current events and be a better informed person
It's seriously a win win
And as always, thank you so much for watching
I don't