this is France
now, i know what you're thinking
if you live in Spain, Italy, Switzerland, Germany, Belgium, the UK, or, god forbid,  within France itself,
then you already know that you're not very far away from france
and if you live somewhere like north america, asia, australia or south america
then you know that you live pretty far away from france
except that that 2nd part isn't really true
because the france i showed you at the beginning isn't really the entirety of france
in reality, france is everywhere across the world, like literally everywhere
here's france in north america
here's france in south america and the caribbean
including this island right here that's divided between france and the netherlands
meaning that france and the netherlands actually do share a border
it's just not in europe, it's in the caribbean
here's france closer to mexico, here's france around madagascar
here's france in the indian ocean and here's france in the pacific ocean
with all of these different locations across the globe
you're probably not as far away from france as you may have thought, if you don't live in europe
inspired by a map i found created by a reddit user named AllHailMadame
let's take a look at how far away you really are from france
colored in black is france itself
within any of the red zones, you are, unfortunately,  less than 1000 km away from sovereign french territory
meaning that you could pretty much begin hearing french at nearly any minute
areas like nova scotia, new brunzwick, quebec, maine, venice, suela, brazil, madagascar, mozambique and south africa
are pretty much all just as far away from actual sovereign france as germany or austria
within the orange zone, you're less than 2000 km away from france
which includes the entire northeastern united states, most of mexico, with the entire caribbean and a whole lot of africa
these zones keep radiating out until we're left with this empty patch here across east asia
within this zone, you're pretty safe because you're more than 7000 km away from any french territory
and it's the furthest possible area away from france you can get anywhere on the planet
spanning across most of china, north korea, the japanese island of okado and far eastern russia
now, the various parts of france that exist all over the world, outside of europe that make all of this possible, are known as overseas france
and it's this other part of france that makes france a true global 21st century great power
altogether, these various islands and landmasses outside of europe
at 119386 km² of territory to the french republic
which is 18 % of france's total land area
and is roughly the same size as either north korea or bulgaria
it's huge and nearly 3 million people live across it all
which is about how many people live in the us state of kansas
and it represents about 4 % of the entire french population
oh yeah and that's the thing, they're all citizens of france
and therefore citizens of the european union by extension as well
which makes all nearly 3 million of them living in places as far away as the caribbean south america and the pacific ocean, all capable of voting in both french and european elections
and because of all these territories existing across the globe
france is actually the country with the highest number of time zones
russia, the world's largest country, spans across only eleven time zones, from west to east
but france, all with her empire cross the world
actually spans across 13 time zones that are shared with places as far away as encourage honolulu
los angeles, new york city, rio de janeiro, paris, obviously
moscow, dubai, karachi, vladiva, stock, sydney and auckland
it appears that in the 21st century, the sun continues to never set on the french empire
but that's all just kind of begs another question
why in the world does france even have an empire but still this vast outside of europe
well, like every other european power
france also got in on the overseas empire game over hundreds of years of progress
with colonies across africa, the middle east in asia
but after world war ii, the world stopped being very sympathetic to colonies
and the colonies of france gradually began declaring their own independences
culminating with france's final colony in africa, gibouti in 1977
and the pacific island of vanuatu in 1980
what remains are the final of vestiges of the ancient french colonial empire that simply never desired independence for themselves
and have thus remained a part of 21st century france
some of them are totally uninhabited
are really only home to seasonal scientists like clipperton island here in the pacific
the various islands of the southern and antarctic lands and adeliland francis claim over antarctica that grants them direct access to the south pole
but all the other places are actually inhabited by permanent populations of people
and some of them are really hugely important places
there's reunion island, way out here, over by madagascar in the indian ocean
with a population of more than 850000 people
which alone is more than two actual eu member states, malta and luxemberg
and nearly as much as a 3rd cyprus, nearby
mayote has an additional population of more than 270000
meaning that there's over a million french citizens living in the indian ocean
were by madagascar in africa
both islands are a fully fledged integral part of france
they use euros
and as such, they're the outermost region of both the european union and the eurozone
like two distant moons orbiting around their faraway planet
reunion is one of the few locations the europeans discovered across the world that was actually truly uninhabi back at the time
and the french acquired it back in the 17th century and have simply kept it ever since
but there's other big locations in frances overseas territories too, like french kiana
way over here in south america, just like reunion
french kayana is an intangural part of france that uses euros and is part of the european union
despite bordering brazil and containing part of the amazon rainforest
this little chunk of europe and france and south america isn't really so little, though
because it's nearly the same size as austria and one 7th the size of metropolitan france itself
back in europe, albeit with a pretty little population of only about 300000 people
which means that the population density throughout is on a par with that's because nearly 99 % of french guiana is completely covered by forests
including the guiana amazonian park
which alone takes up more than 40 % of french guiana
and is, hilariously, the largest national park of the european union
despite, well, you know, being located in south america
french guiana is immensely important to both france and europe today
because it is the primary launch site for rockets of the european space agency, are esa
and it's specifically because of french geographic location
look at this map of the world
and then think to yourself
where are the best locations possible to blast rockets off in a space from
the correct answer is as close as you can get to the equator across the earth's center
and it's because here along this line, the planet is rotating faster than anywhere else
rockets need all the speed they can get in order to break out of our gravity
and the earth's natural rotation speed can give them a much needed boost
unfortunately for europe, the equator runs pretty considerably far away from their continents
which makes blasting rockets off from there a little more challenging
but fortunately for europe, they spent centuries taking over colonies in other parts of the world
and it turned out that french guiana, in particular, is located really, really close to the equator
and so that's how this little chunk of south america became europe's most important spaceport
it's so important that at one point back in the 1990s
the guiana space center alone accounted for more than a quarter of french guiana's entire gdp
all right, so moving on over to the pacific
france retains possessions of hundreds of islands and talls across french polynesia
in caledonia, wallison, futuna and clipperton island
including the island of bora, bora, inside a french polynesia
which is one of france's most popular tourist destinations
despite being located on the complete opposite side of the world from paris
but the pacific part of france carries a darker secret than the other parts of overseas france does because it was here that france primarily conducted their decades long nuclear weapons testing
back in 1960, when the french empire still spanned much more of the globe
france became the 4th country to successfully test in detonated nuclear weapon
after the united states, soviet union and united kingdom
but they did so initially within the empty deserts of algeria, awkwardly
at the same time that algeria was fighting a war against france for their own independence
france would go on to detonate a total of 17 nuclear weapons inside of the empty deserts of algeria before it became an independent nation
after which, they subsequently refused to continue allowing france to test their nukes there
so still one in a test their bomb somewhere
they began looking for alternatives
one such idea was to begin testing them on the uninhabited clipperton island, nearby to mexico
but this was ruled out because of the island's intense level of remoteness
and also mexico probably would have had a thing or two to say about it
eventually, france settled on continuing their nuclear weapons testing over in french polynesia
where a total of 193 three detonations would be carried out in the pacific ocean nearby
which brought france directly into conflict with nearby new zealand in 1985
back then
the organization greenpeace orchestrated a campaign against the continued french nuclear testing in the area with a boat called the rainbow warrior
which was docked in port inside of auckland
new the ship was about to depart towards french polynesia to protest against a planned french nuclear test
when two undercover french operatives secretly snug on board
planted a bomb and then blew the ship apart
the explosion sank the ship and killed a green piece photographer who was on board
the french agents were quickly apprehended afterwards by the new zealand police
and were each sentenced to ten years in prison for manslaughter
they would ultimately only serve for two years before being freed by the french government
many political figures, especially in new zealand
have consistently referred to the action ever since as an incident of french states sponsored terrorism
and france would ultimately agree to pay million dollars in damages to greenpeace
along with million dollars to the new zealand government as an apology
and a further half a million dollars to the photographer's family as compensation
france would continue testing nuclear weapons in polynesia for eleven more years
until in 1996, the year of their final detonation
and ever since
they've switched to using computer simulations for their nuclear weapons testing instead
and today
france maintains an arsenal of approximately 300 nuclear weapons
the 3rd largest arsenal in the world, after the united states and russia
so that was one the reason that france kept much of their overseas empire
but overall
the biggest reason why france maintains the overseas empire up to the present is because of the control that it gives france and the european union as a proxy over the world's oceans
you see, under the terms of the united nations convention on the law of the sea or unclose
any country may claim an exclusive economic zone or eeg of the water surrounding their sovereign coastline
the country making the claim retains the sole and exclusive legal authority for all fishing
drilling, mining and all other economic activities
and because of there are hundreds of islands and territories that are scattered across all the corners of the earth
france actually possesses the modern world's largest eeg
and therefore the largest maritime territory of any 20 st century nation
ahead of even the united states and australia
france's eeg spans nearly 11.7 million km² of ocean, across the bay of this sky, the indian ocean
while almost completely surrounding madagascar, huge blotches of the pacific ocean
and even a tiny little sliver here just south of canada
these small islands are st pierre and megalone
and despite being located right next to newfoundland and canada
they're a part of france, then home to more than french citizens who all use years
they are the small, final remaining vestiges of the old colonial new france in the americas
and they have a fascinating history of control
when france was defeated in the seven years war back in 1763
they were forced to seed all of their north american possessions over to the british
but since the british continued to grant the french fishing rights along the newfoundland coast
they allowed them to keep the tiny islands as a little fishing outpost
when france supported america during the american revolution, burton invaded the islands
raised the settlement and exiled the entire french population back to european france
out of spite, burton tried to bring in british settlers to repopulate the islands
but then the french came back and sacked the british column
eventually, the british gave the islands back to france once again in 1802
but then, after war with napoleon interrupted, they reoccupied them again the very next year
in 1803, when the napoleonic wars were concluded
eleven years later
and 18 and 14, the british once again gave the islands back to france
but then occupied them again in 1815, when napoleon briefly returned to power in france
and then gave them back to france yet again, after he was defeated after waterloo, for good
and theyve been french ever since
during the 1st world war, all of the men on the islands were drafted
and about 400 went on to serve on the western front in europe, where a quarter of them would die
when the topic of eegs came up in the 1970s
france initially claimed a huge one for the tiny little islands that severely interrupted nearby canada's e-e-z
which led to a very long legal dispute between both countries over fishing rights
it was only eventually settled in 1992 when france accepted the significantly smaller and narrower boundaries of the current eeg here
but it's still kind of weird
because now the french control this zone where they're the only ones who are allowed to fish
and it's completely surrounded by the zone where the canadians are the only ones who are allowed to fish
so canadian fishermen have to always move around it
and local french fishermen are always confined within it
but when zooming back out again to see the full picture, francis, the oceanic territory
all combined across the world, is larger than the entirety of the european continent itself
and france possesses 8 % of the entire world's e easy areas
despite the fact that france itself only possesses zero point 45 % of the world's land and only 84 % of the world's population
if you were to combine both land and maritime area for every country in the world, then france
all of a sudden ranks as the world's 5th largest country
beating up places like brazil, china, india or indonesia
which is, frankly, just ridiculous
and it all gives france and, by extension
the european union an enormous global geopolitical advantage
when also factoring in spains, portugals, the netherlands and denmarks overseas territories
the european union's collective e-e-z enables it to dominate the entire baltic control
nearly the entire mediterranean and the eastern north of atlantic
and have outposts across every ocean and every corner of the globe
after the united kingdom and the united states
france even further maintains the 3rd largest amount of overseas military bases outside of their home territory
with bases all across their overseas possessions in south america
the caribbean, indian and pacific ocean
with even further bases across many of their former colonies in africa
like jibouti, ivory, coast, gabone, senegal, mali, chad, niger
additional bases across the middle east, in syria, iraq, jordan and the uae
and a final two more inside of germany
altogether
france maintains a force of more than 36000 soldiers deployed to these territories across the world
and ever since
the french have initiated military interventions across these nine countries on two separate continents
the presence of these french military bases and soldiers all across the world
from south america to africa
the middle east and the pacific gives the french a very similar capability the united states
they can project power and deploy military assets at a moment's notice to counter almost any threat anywhere on the planet
so when you look at a map like this, you realize that the global french
and therefore the global european empire, is very much still alive and well in the 21st century
and as as a result, france and europe are probably a lot closer to you than you may have realized
but something else you may haven't realized yet is just how much you're probably over paying for your current cell phone plan
and how much you could save by switching over to team
i personally switched over to team myself a few months ago
and why
well, because of this, yep
that's actual a real phone bill that i received for my old carrier right before i made my switch earlier this year
but team mobile has three different plans to choose from to make sure that never happens again
unlimited talk in text starts at just $10
and then datas $5 a gigabyte
or you can just get their unlimited plan for just $45
they've also got other plans with five or twelve
it invites data
but regardless
the point is that you can get the same service you have right now with the same phone number you have right now
for much less money
so if you've ever got a bill like mine, your service probably won't change
it's pretty much a no brainer
but what should really seal the deal is that when you click the button that's on your screen right now or follow the link that's down in the description
you'll get totally free $25 credit, enough for an entire month of service on some of their plans
and signing up there really helps to support real life law at the same time
and as always, thank you so much for watching