las vegas is one of the most well known cities anywhere in the world
tens of millions of people visited every single year, who contribute to making it the 3rd most visited city in the united states by foreign tourists, just behind new york
in miami, las vegas received so many foreign tourists that it beats out many other major the tourists taught spot cities across the world, like los angeles, chicago, shanghai, barcelona, berlin, vienna and even venice
in order to accommodate all these visitors, las vegas possesses a truly impressive hospitality arsenal of around 150000 hotel rooms, which is more than any other city on the planet
planet is gods. and this is despite the fact that las vegas itself is a relatively young city, having only existed for a tad longer than a century, and with a relatively small metropolitan population of only a little more than million people, which only ranks it as the 26th largest in the united states, las vegas's size and age are irrelevant factors to the massive volumes of tourists who arrive here every single year
for them, they almost all come for just one single thing vegas's legendary reputation as the entertainment capital of the world and the the greatest playground for adults anywhere on the earth
along with louisiana, the state of nevada, where las vegas is located, is the only american state to a fully legalized casino gambling statewide, which has long caused vegas to be almost synonymous with gambling and casinos
around eight in every ten visitors the city will gamble at one of the numerous casinos while they're there, and bet an average of around 600 a person, while slightly more than half of all visitors will attend one of the many shows hosted in the city as well
altogether, these tourists visiting the city generally contribute more than 100 billion dollars per year to the nevada state economy and place las vegas as one of the top travel destinations in the world
but the strangest aspect of the city for me, as someone who spent much of their childhood growing up in nevada, with more visits to las vegas than i can even count, is the fact that all of this outrageous entertainment and excess for tens of millions of people all seemingly exists precisely where it shouldn't, in the middle of the dryest and least hospitable desert of the north american continent, the mohave desert
this is the same desert that includes death valley, after all, the ominously and appropriately named valley, located just a two hour drive from the las vegas strip, the hottest temperature ever measured on the surface of the earth, a little more than a century ago in 1913, at 134 degrees fahrenheit, or 57 degrees celsius, the mohave desert is so dry that the area around las vegas itself only receives an average of around 4 " of rainfall per year, which is even less rain than timbuktu receives in mali, at the southern edge of the sahara desert
in 2020, las vegas set a still standing record of going 224 entire straight days without a single drop of rainfall
and the reason for las vegas' extreme dryness is almost entirely geographical
the mojave desert itself is located entirely east of the towering sierra nevada mountains of california, with peaks as high as mount whitney at 14505 ft, the highest point anywhere in the contiguous 48 united states, and a mere 85 mi away, as the crow flies from from the affir mentioned death valley, the lowest point on the north american continent, at 282 ft
beneath sea level. these towering mountains block most of the moisture that blows into north america from the westerly winds of the pacific, and they therefore cast what's known as a rain shadow across their east where the moisture coming in from the pacific fails to penetrate into of course, las vegas itself is located directly within this rain shadow cast by the sierra nevada, but it's also located within a valley here that's surrounded by even further mountain ranges on every side, some of which sore up to 10000 ft in elevation and block even more moisture from blowing into the city with the wind from beyond
and the nearest significant river and source of fresh water to this valley, the colorado, is around 30 mi away from it
in short, this valley was never, historically, a very attractive location to build even a settlement, and much less of modern metropolis of two and a quarter mill and as a result, it was basically nothing of any more significance than sparsely populated desert for thousands of years, until the very beginning of the 20th century, when the city of las vegas was officially founded in 1905 and incorporated in 1911
but for the next several decades
afterwards, vegas would remain relatively sleepy and quiet until 1931, when two major things happened that would change the region's demographic destiny forever
afterwards, with a tiny population of only 94000 people statewide, nevada was by far
the least popular state in the country at the time, with less than half the population of the next least popular state, wyoming, reeling from the economic fallout of the great depression, and struggling to find anyone who is willing to invest in their tiny state economy, the nevada state government decided on a bold course of action
they became the 1st u-s state to legalize nearly every form of gambling in order to bring in at least some kind of economic relief to their state
and perhaps even more importantly, 1931 also marked the beginning of the construction of the hoover dam on the colorado river, just 30 mi away from the city
and perhaps even more importantly, never before in human history had such a mono the alithic structure, ever been built with concrete
thousands of laborers moved in and worked higherlessly for years to finish the job, and at least 115 of them lost their lives trying
but with thousands of new workers coming into the town for the dam construction came higher demands for things like entertainment and amenities
and with the recently legalization of casino gambling, the genesis for las vegas' status as the entertainment capital of the world was born
when the dam was finished in 1936, it created the largest water reservoir in the entire united states
just behind it in the form of lake mead, and granted the southwestern united states the ability to generate enormous amounts of electricity through hydropower
the colorado river is ideally suited for hydroelectric power generation, owing to its large flow and steep gradient, descending from its source high up in the rocky mountains of colorado towards the lower elevations of the mohave and sonoran deserts, with massive volumes of water pumped to the city directly from lake mead
and massive amounts of electricity from the dam investment finally began pouring into and its unique entertainment industry following the 2nd world war, and the population began to steadily increase
by 1960, wats vegas had finally overtaken reno to become nevada's most popular city with 64000 people, and the population would roughly double from there over the next decade to more than 125000 people by 1970, more people that lived in the entirety of nevada just 30 years previously
from then, back in 1940, between 19 92000, the population of las vegas roughly doubled again, and by the close of the 20th century, las vegas had earned the distinction of being the most populous city in north america, founded within the same century, just like chicago had been during the 19th century
but as las vegas's fortunes and population continue to soar, so too did the demand in the region for the area sparse supplies of water
with its crippling lack of rainfall, the population of las vegas and southern nevada is overwhelmingly dependent upon lake mead and the colorado river that feeds it from the snow melt of the rocky mountains, accounting for some 90 % of all the city's fresh water today
back in the 1920s, prior to the construction of the hoover dam, the seven american states, the controlled territory within the colorado rivers basin, agreed to the colorado river at agreement the divided control of the waters within the basin amongst all seven of the states
the upper states of colorado, utah wyoming in new mexico would be entitled to roughly half of the colorado rivers water, while the lower states of california, arizona and nevada would be entitled to the other half, with nearly 59 % of that half going to california, 37 % arizona and just 4 % nevada
but the realities of the 1920s were very different from the realities of today
one of the biggest concerns of the agreement, both then and now, was the expanding population in the southwest, particularly in southern california, and the resulting increase demand over time for water in the lower basin states
at the same time, las vegas wasn't even really a factor at all back in the 1920s, with a population of less than 3000 people, with a modern population well in excessive over 2 million
nevada has been looking for an increased share in the river's water now for decades, but today, there are more than 40 million people who depend on the colorado river for their water supply, and las vegas is only a small fraction of that
and at the same time, the colorado the river's water has actually been greatly over allocated for decades now, because the original estimates of the compact back in the 1920s suggested that the river had an annual average flow of about 17 and a half million acre feet of water that reached the lower basin seats of arizona, nevada and california
however, these estimates back at the time were based on just the past 30 years of records going back to the 1890s
which were all the records that the people of the 1920s
actually had
available. and modern 21st century studies of trade rings in the area have revealed that those 30 years of records they used
just so what will happen to probably be the wettest period in the american southwest, any time in the past five to twelve centuries
in other words, the authors of the 1920s era compact were grossly misinformed on the actual historical average levels of water within the river
and more water has been being allocated to the states around it then actually exists within the river almost ever since
and then climate change decreased rates of snowfall in the rocky mountains, and droughts have been making everything much worse
and the situation has now gotten so bad that the colorado river today rarely even is enough flow left in it to make it to its natural delta in the gulf of california in mexico, where the one's rich natural environment has almost completely died there and dried up
this also means the lake meat itself, the source of most of modern las vegas's fresh water, is rapidly shrinking in size
last month, in june of 2022, the reservoir hit a new all time low after losing nearly 180 ft
of depth over just the past 20 years
if the levels dropped by another hundred feet, the hoover dam will no longer be capable of producing any hydroelectric power
but as it has always done now for the past century, las vegas is rapidly learning how to adapt to this changing environment
and fascinatingly, despite being well renowned as a city of tremendous successes, las vegas is one of the most water efficient cities in the entire world, because they have no other choice but to be remember when i said the nevada is only allocated percent of the lower colorado rivers water
that amounts to just around 300000 acre feet of water today, which isn't really when considering the california takes more than 14 times that amount from the river
but the catch is that so long as the water is returned back to the river, it doesn't actually count against the state in terms of total consumption
this loophole means that the southern nevada water authority will usually draw around 445000 an acre feet of water from lake mead during a normal year, or about 40 % more than they're technically allotted for
but since the city is capable of cleaning and returning around 220000 acre feet of water back to lake me during the same year, nevada's total consumption from the river is usually more like just 225000 feet and well beneath their total allotment
in order to achieve this incredible rate of water recycling, the city of las vegas has enacted a number of ingenious policy and engineering decisions
the city has been designed in such a way that every last drop of water that ends up being used indoors gets cleaned, cycled directly back to lake mead
you could quite literally turn on every single shower and every single sink in every hotel room in the city, and it wouldn't ever consume any more water, because it would all just flow through the city sewers directly to water treatment plants, and then directly return all clean back to lake need for future use
and further watering lawns within the city limits was strictly limited to just a single day a week
and largely because of this focus on sustainable desert design, las vegas actually managed to reduce their total water consumption dramatically by 26 % over the the past 20 years, since 2002, despite having added an additional 750000 new residents to the total population of the city over the same time period
and they aren't finished reducing their water consumption either
the 1st type of law of its kind in the united states, las vegas banned nonfunctional and decorative grass in the city last year, in 2021
to save even more water, grass is beginning torn out across city, own property across las vegas ever since, and it's going to make an enormous difference
1 sq ft. of grass consumes 73 gallons of water a year in order to keep alive, while more drought tolerant desert landscaping only consumes 18 gallons a year
city officials are spending millions of dollars trying to convince current homeowners to tear out their grass lawns and replace them with more water friendly desert landscaping options
the southern nevada water authority believes that these simple landscaping measures, favoring sustainable desert landscaping over nonfunctional grass, will save around nine and a half billion gallons of water a year, which is nearly 10 % of las vegasist total water supply
in a lot of senses, las vegas is the model city for the rest of the southwestern united states, as the region faces increasingly harsher drought conditions and decreasing water supplies
as the american government just recently issued its 1st ever declared water shortage for the colorado river
this year, it has cut water allocations all the states along the river, including nevadas, from 300000 acre feet to just 279000 acre feet, which, when factoring in the rate of las vegas' incredible rate of water recycling, is still enough to meet current demand
but for how much longer? many climate experts are warning that water levels within the colorado basin will likely continue to drop over the next several decades, when combined with the ever increasing demand for water from the still growing population across southern nevada, arizona and southern california, the life for the desert communities here are almost certainly going to continue growing ever more challenging from a water security perspective
the fact simply is that in the future, the other cities of the american southwest and everywhere else in the world who will struggle with water supplies in the near future should look to las vegas for their inspiration of a city well designed to cope with the challenges of 21st century climate change, in the middle of one of earth's least hospitable desert environments, for if life can be sustained for millions of people and tens of millions of visitors here, through decades of clever design and foresight, it can also be achieved elsewhere
now, a major reason that i was so excited to make a video covering this topic is because i knew that i could get all kinds of spectacular footage of las vegas and the colorado river without actually having to go travel and visit them myself by simply visiting my stock footage provider
instead, storedlocks without any exaggeration. since the very 1st real life lore videos that i created more than six years ago
now, story blocks has always been the 1st place that i've always gone to find footage for all of my videos
they offer an unlimited subscription so that you can download and use as much as you need for an annual price that's lower than what many other providers charge for just a single clip
and beyond that, unlimited subscription, storyblocks also offers an entirely royalty free library, meaning that you can use anything from the library for any commercial or personal use
and storeblocks offers far more than just footage and templates
they also provide music, images, sound effects and much more
if you're already a creator or you're wanting to become one, i can absolutely tell you, from my more than six years of experience now, is their customer that story blocks is an absolutely critical resource for you to have
i genuinely don't think i know of a single full time creator who doesn't already have a subscription
so if you'd like to get started with them as well, click the button that's here on screen right now, or head over to storyblocks coms last real life floor to sign up
and by doing so, you'll also be greatly supporting my channel at the same time while you're at it
and as always, thank you so much for watching
yeah