of all the world's continents, australia may be the
smallest, but it's also the only one to be entirely controlled by just a single country
almost everybody knows, though, that while
australia is a huge place in terms of land, it's also a pretty small place in terms of population
but few people really understand the absolute scale of how sparsely populated the australian continent actually is
to help put the numbers in a some perspective, australia is of a comparable size to the lower 48 u-s states
these 48 u-s states have a population of more than three hundred million people, while australia only has a population of little more than 26 million
this means that there are two american states that have more people than the entirety of the australian continents, california with more than 39 million, and texas, with more than 28 million
for a more european perspective, the population of only england, without factoring in any of the rest of the uk, is more than double the entire population of australia
despite being an entire continent. there are actually seven significantly smaller islands across the world that have higher populations than australia
great britain, of course, along with hanshu luzan, mindinal java, sumatra and madagascar
java alone has nearly six times australia's tiny population, despite being an island that is 60 times smaller than australia the continents
but it still gets even crazier, because there's also a bunch of cities across the world that right now have more people than the entire continent as well
the tokyo, jakarta and delhi metropolitan areas all have greater populations than the entirety of australia
well, the shanghai and soul metro areas have roughly similar populations
sao paulo, mexico city, new york city, cairo, lagos, mumbai and moscow all have largely comparable metropolitan populations to australia as well
and all things considered, australia really only has five actual major cities across their continent, sydney, melbourne, brisbane, perth and adelaide, which collectively account for the residences of nearly two out of every three australians
australia is therefore among the most heavily urbanized nations in the world, with the overwhelming majority of the population, around 90 %, concentrated into relatively small urban areas that only account for 0.22 % of australias total land area, with half of the overall population living within just these red areas, and the other half almost entirely living in these blue areas
overall, around 85 % of all australians live within just 50 km of the coastline, meaning that there's hardly anyone deeper into the continents vast interior
this unique population distribution creates a lot of fascinatingly bizarre situations across the continents
e.g. this is the shire of east pillpara in western australia
it is roughly the same size as japan, but there's only a bit more than 10000 people who live here
and have half of them just live right here in the town of newman
it's basically just a small town, but with the space of japan
then, perhaps even more strangely, there's the pastoral unincorporated area down here in south australia
this dot is the city of adelaide australia's 5th largest city, home to more than million people
an immediately adjacent to this oasis of urban life is the pastoral unincorporated area, a territory that's roughly the size of france, but is only home to a whopping 3750 people, making the population density something like 178 km²
of land. for every one person
that is roughly one aruba's worth of land for every single resident inside of the pastoral unincorporated area
then there's also anna creek right over here
this is a huge territory that's slightly larger than israel, and yet it is in a country or even a governmental entity at all
no anna creek is actually just a privately owned cattle ranch, the largest cattle ranch found anywhere in the world by far, that is only staffed by eight full time employees, according to wikipedia
so this entire area that's the size of israel is usually only home to less than a dozen people and around 10000 cows
australia is really, really, really empty
and to hammer the point home even further, consider the towns of aspirants on the south coast and kunonura, near to the north coast
both of these towns are within the same state of western australia, and it takes at least 30 5 h of time to drive from one to the other, across a distance of more than 30 200 km
and along that
entire distance in time, you'll maybe only drive through a population of less than 70000 people the entire way
for comparison, this drive would be about the same one time and distance is driving from madrid to istanbul, across nearly the whole of europe, where there would be a lot more than 70000 people
so what is it about australia that makes it such an overall empty void of people
what is it about this continent that has made everything i just brought up possible
well, the easy answer that i'm sure most of you are thinking right now is the desert
da everybody knows that australia is covered in a big old desert with tons of super dangerous animals and insects who would ever want to actually live in most of the country
and while there is some truce to this line of thinking, i'm here to argue with you that that's only a small part of the overall population puzzle in australia, and the full explanation for why there are so few people on this continent is, overall a pretty complicated one
most of the problem stems from the fact that australia is pretty uniquely cursed when it comes to both geologic and location perspective
located relatively close by to antarctica, the frozen continent, the western side of australia is continuously battered by cold ocean currents coming up from the southern ocean, which means that there simply isn't enough heat to generate large scale evaporation that's necessary to form rain clouds over much of the west
meanwhile, in the east, the great dividing range is australia's largest and longest chain of mountains, and the 5th longest anywhere in the world
these mountains run down the entire eastern side of the continent, from north to south, and their height denies many rain clouds advancing from the pacific the ability to move move any further into australia than the immediate and narrow band of land between the mountains and the coastline
thus, a so called rain shadow is cast by these mountains across the vastness of the australian interior to the west, where moisture coming in from the east understandably struggles to penetrate into
but these mountains, generally speaking, from a global perspective, aren't really all that impressive
truly big mountains cannot be found anywhere on the surface of australia
and overall, the continent has the lowest average elevation of all of earths continents, which just creates a further, huge problem for rainfall
the tallest mountain and highest point that can be found anywhere in mainland australia is here within the great dividing range
now kaziasco, and it's only 2228 m high above sea level
for comparison, the highest point of every single other inhabited continent is at least more than double that height
and nearly three quarters of the entire us state of colorado alone maintains an elevation that is significantly higher than just that one sort of tall mountain in australia
this means that there are simply very few tall mountains to be found anywhere on the continent that are actually capable of forcing air upwards where it's possible to cool into rain, and then to make matters even worse, that air is very often just too hot for rain form anyway, because the continent straddles the boundary of the tropic of capricorn, placing a significant amount of northern australia to be well within the tropics, and almost the rest of the continent down on the subtropic
this area of the world is dominated by the sub tropical high pressure belt that wraps around the entire glow, and it simultaneously serves to both warm and dry the air around it
so whatever air even does get pushed up by the few tall mountains in australia has to also contend with this phenomenon
and what's even more, australia has to also contend with the difficult to predict oscillations of the southern pacific ocean, known as el nino and lanenia
during an el nino event, which can sometimes last for years at a time, the southern pacific often goes through prolonged periods of slower than usual westerly winds, and that, not naturally, means that there will be less atmospheric moisture delivered by those winds to the eastern and northern parts of the australian continent, often accompanied by exacerbated, drought like conditions
it's unsurprising, then, that many of the worst bush fires in australia's history have taken place at the exact same time as during one of these el nino events
all of these factors converged to make australia, by far the dryest inhabited continent on the earth, with the least amount of average annual rainfall
and consequently, desert or desert light conditions understandably exist over about 35 % of the continent continents total area
i mean, just take a look at this map of australia's average rates of annual rainfall, where you can see most of the rain on the continent falls on the east coast, in the stretch of land between the coastline and the great dividing range in the north that stretches into the tropics, tasmania in the south and around perth in the southwest corner
it's basically an identical map with australia's current population density pattern, except in one very interesting and notable area, northern australia
the problem up here is not that it receives a low amount of rain on average, but that it receives that rain largely all at once and over ridiculously variable periods of time, just like everywhere else in the tropics
northern australia is dominated by the wet and the dry season, where
rainfall is greater during the summer and less during the winter
in the cave of darwin, the largest city up here on australia's northern coast, the average annual rainfall amount is more than 1800 mm, which is nearly triple the amount of rainfall that london gets
however, the vast majority of that rain falls during just the four months of the wet season, between december and march, when the areas march soons and tropical cyclones are generally active
and when you discount the immediate coastline, the rest of northern australia and the interior between the coast and the north and the tropic of capricorn in the south, suffers from some of the most highly erratic rainfalls seen anywhere on the planet, largely owing to the unpredictable pattern of in the areas tropical cyclones
in 1898, one of these cyclones dumped an absolutely unbelievable 740 mm
of rain over this small northern australia town in just a single day, more than the entire average annual rainfall of london
which could give the false impression, if you just looked at that single year, of more rainfall here than in the uk
but then a few decades later on, in 1924, without any cyclones penetrating through to the interior here, this town only received 4 mm
of rain throughout the whole year, which is even less than the yearly average of the sahara desert
but it's not just the erratic nature of the continent's rainfall that makes fresh water escape
it's also the lack of any decently large rivers
the most significant river system on the continent is the murray darling base, and here in the southeast, in one of australia's most heavily populated cores
but it just kind of sucks from a build a big civilization perspective
1st of all, the waters of the system flow southwestward and empty out right here on the south coast
this isn't really good, because it's mentioned previously
most of this basin exists in the part of australia beyond the great dividing range, that doesn't usually see a lot of rainfall to replenish the rivers with water
as a result, the average annual flow of the waters in the basin amounts to just 24000 giga leaders a year, which is the lowest rate of flow of any of the world's greatest river systems
for comparison, the mississippi basin in the united states has an average annual flow of nearly 530000 a year, which is more than 22 times the flow of water that australia's greatest river system has got
nonetheless, it's the best that the continent has got
and the basin provides the drinking water for around 3 million australians today, while the area around it has developed into the agricultural heartland of the modern australia nation, providing nearly the entirety of the food that the 26 million people of australia consume, along with enough to export to millions more across asia
but as climate change continues to worsen the effects of drought in the continent, the waters that feed this agricultural hartland, through the murray darling basin, are getting harder and harder to come by
with every passing decade. nine of the ten hottest recorded years in the continents history have taken place just since 2005
these higher temperatures are rapidly increasing the rates of evaporation throughout the waters of the basin, and with already limited rainfall throughout the majority of it, it's making the water here increasingly scarce, with some sections of the basin, at times, remaining completely dry for months on end
and it's not just the scarcity of fresh water on the continent that makes sustaining a very large population difficult
it's also the scarcity of good land for farming in agriculture, owing once again, largely to geography, geology and location
in northern australia, there hasn't been any new mountain buildings since the pre cambrian era, that ended one and a half billion years ago
and even further, there hasn't been any glacial activity here since the carboniferous ended nearly 300 million years ago
thus, this entire region that covers nearly half of the continent has suffered its soils being beneath continuous weathering, an erosion for well over million years, compared to less than 10000 years for most of the soils on other continents, like north america, europe or asia
therefore, the soil nearly everywhere in northern australia just sucks for agriculture
the only exception of that rule is the area of the river base in the drains here in lake erie
but this is an overall small amount of the north, and the rainfall required for irrigation
here is still very low. but the thing is, none of these geographic or
climatic explanations really give the full picture
because
despite everything that i just spent the last 10 min explaining to you, it turns out that australia actually has a
ton of fresh water resources, well, at least one compared to countries, and not to continents
in fact, australia has an estimated 492 cubic kilometers worth of renewable freshwater resources, which is more than a lot of countries with significantly higher populations
that's twice as much as pakistan, e.g., a country which has more than eight times as many people
so it's not just a sheer lack of fresh water
and it's not just a sheer lack of arable land either
while yeah, only about 6 % of australia's land is actually arable and suitable for agriculture, australia is huge, so that 6 % is still a ton of usable farmland
to put it in a context, australia has more arable land than indonesia, malaysia, singapore, the philippines, vietnam, cambodia and laos all have combined, despite all of these countries having a combined population of 542000000 people, and australia only having 26 million people
to put it into another perspective, australia has by far the highest ratio in the entire world of arable land to population, at around 1.9 arable hectares of land for every one citizen of the country
for the sake of comparison, the ratio in the united states is only about zero point, 47 arable hectares of land per one citizen
this means that if australia ever reached the same ratio of arable land to people as the united states, the continent would be home to well over 90 million people, still substantially less than the population of america, but also substantially more people than australia has today
in theory, australia does have enough of space and resources to support a lot more people than the 26 million who live there today
the big reason why it doesn't is because for pretty much the entire history of australia, right up until the present day, it's just been a really tough place for anyone to actually get to
you see, for millions of years now, australia has been effectively a lost continent, isolated from all the earth's southern major landmasses, drifting alone out in the sea
this has resulted in millions of years of completely separate evolution for the animals of the continent, which is why australia's unique among earth's continents for the fact that marsupials, and not central mammals, dominate the indigenous mammal wildlife species
modern humans 1st reached the continent sometime around 50000 years ago, when the areas' geography looked radically different than it does today, with sea levels significantly lower
back then, humans were able to simply walk down the sunda peninsula, pop a few islands, then make it into present day new guinea, which back then was connected to australia via land bridge, as the prehistoric continent of sahul
and after these initial humans made it to the continent, they remained almost entirely undisturbed for tens of thousands of years by any other groups of humans from anywhere in the outside world
as sea levels began to rise following the end of the last ice age, sohoul was flooded, and the land bridge between new guinea and australia fell beneath the waves around 10000 years ago, making australia even more remote than it had been previously, and even less likely to ever be visited by outside for the next 90 600 years, before the eventual arrival of the europeans in the 17th century, the australian continents may have only been significantly visited and impacted by outside humans, a total of just two times
dingoes, an invasive species of dog like the originating from new guinea
we're introduced to australia some time around years ago, potentially by an unknown group of human visitors coming from the island
about percent of the modern aboriginal australian dna also derives from indians, which suggests a potential encounter on the continent with a group of humans from south asia some time around 4000 years ago
and then, after millennia of existing almost entirely undisturbed by the outside world, in 1606, a dutchman and his crew suddenly showed up on their ships and landed right here on the western side of the cape york peninsula
but even after that, the dutch never really bothered ever establish any permanent settlements or presence on the continent, because the parts of it that they found were generally decided to be too uninhabitable
for all the reasons i mentioned during the 1st half of this video, the closest the dutch ever came to a permanent settlement on australia, happened entirely by accident
50 years after their discovery, in 1656, a dutch ship called the vergoulda dryak, crashed off the coast of western australia
around here, 75 of the ship survivors miraculously made
it to the shore, and then seven of them were dispatched on one of the ship's life boats to make the 14 hundred mile long journey, journey over to batavia, or modern day jacarta, on the island of java, which was the administrative capital of colonial dutch
rule in indonesia at the time
after 41 grueling days of travel, these seven people finally made it to batavia and raised the alarm for the 68 crew and passengers who they left behind back in australia
and for the next several years, numerous search and rescue missions were carried out by the dutch navy all along the western australian coast
the little sign of the ship's wreckage was ever discovered, and the 68 survivors of the virgodadraia who were left behind were simply never seen heard from again, their ultimate fates remaining a mystery to this day, they simply vanished into the vast void of australia and history without much of a trace
more than three centuries of time would pass before finally, in 1963, the wreckage of the virgguda dryac was covered by a team of australian divers roughly 100 km north of modern day's per well over a century after the vanishing of the virgoda, 68 on the continent, the british finally established the 1st truly permanent european settlement in australia only in 1788, over on the complete other side of the continent, around modern day sydney, with the around 1300 people time
the aboriginal population of the continent was likely only somewhere around 650000, which was pretty much the entire population of australia as a whole
to put that in a perspective, every other inhabited continent on the planet had vastly, vastly more people than that
1788, asia already had more than 650000000 people, around a thousand times the population of australia, while europe and nearly 150000000 africa had 85 million in the americas had around 20 million
australia therefore began the modern era of industrialization from a far, far lower population base than any other of earth's inhabited continents
and since population growth tends to be exponential, australia has been lagging behind the rest for centuries
in 1788, the population of the freshly independent united states stood at around 4 million people
it would take australia, australia more than a century of history, not until the year 1906, to finally surpass the population of the united states back in 1788
and by 1906, america's population was already pushing 90 million
for most of australia's history, immigration came almost entirely, clearly from just a single source, the british isles
following the discovery of gold on the continent in 1851, a massive gold rush to australians sued
that's all around 2 % of the entire population of the british isles emigrate to australia throughout the decade of the 1850s, and more than doubled the australian population almost overnight
but australia struggled to attract large numbers of immigrants from europe afterwards, because it was heavily competing for them with more attractive countries in the americas, like the united states, canada, brazil and argentina, who were much closer to europe geographically, and were thus generally cheaper and quick for europeans to emigrate to
it didn't help that beginning in the australian government enacted a policy that would artificially reduce their numbers of immigrants to the continent
for decades, the racist white australia policy, which restricted immigration to only people of white european ancestry, and initially gave overwhelming preference to migrants coming specifically from britain
as a result, the flow of immigrants to the continent remained only a trickle of people for decades across the early 20th century, while at the same time, millions of immigrants were arriving in the united states every couple of years
the population of australia even shrank during world war one, when nearly one in five australia's men were shipped off to fight the war in europe
around two and a half percent of australia's entire male population of the time never made it back home from the trenches and beaches of europe
by the eve of world war ii, australia was a small and overwhelmingly european nation of only around 7 million on the periphery of asia
and many white australians of the time were terrified of being demographically overwhelmed by the extreme only more populous nations of asia just to the north
by the time war came to the continent, imperial japan had more than ten times australia's population, at more than 73 million
and after the japanese bombed the northern australian city of darwin in 1942, fears across the continent were rife that imminent japanese invasion was coming
and
while the invasion never actually materialized, the australian government nonetheless came to believe that they needed to
increase their population to avoid the threat of another invasion
scare like that again in the future
before 1945, almost all the immigrants to australia came from either great britain or ireland
but after the war
australia, for the very 1st time, began encouraging immigration from across the european continent
the policies restricting immigration, largely only to britains, were gradually relaxed to be more inclusive of all europeans, and by the 1960s, 3 million mainland europeans from places like the baltic states, poland, italy, the balkans and greece, packed up their bags and headed to australia to begin a brand new life, many of them being displaced refugees from the war
but the exclusion of non whites as immigrants of the continent remained large largely enforce for several more decades, even after the war
it wasn't until 1973, nearly three decades after the end of world war ii, that the white australia policy was finally overturned, and race ceased being a factor in the continents
immigration policy since australia has maintained an official policy of multiculturalism and is welcomed large scale multi ethnic immigration for decades from all across the world
and now in the 20 st century, the vast majority of new immigrants to the continent come from asia, and not from europe, especially from china and india
today, australia caps the new numbers of immigrants to the continent at less than 200000 a year
which for a country of only 26 million is actually a pretty consistently high rate of immigration
as of 2022, nearly one in three people on the australian continent was born outside of it, which is by far the highest proportion of immigrants found in the population of any developed western nation
australia today is a proud nation of immigrants from all across the world, and by 2050, the continents population is protected to increase up to around 36 million, about the same as canada today, and largely through continued immigration
but the growth over the next two decades will not come without its challenges
the continents ancient natural challenges like unpredictable rainfall, dry rivers, droughts and vast arid wilderness, along with new challenges like the uncertain course of climate change, mean that australia has an epic battle against its own environment ahead of it to continue increasing their population
but despite all the odds that are stacked up against them, the country is actually one of the world's most major agricultural producers and exporters, with more than 104000000 sheep on the continents, there are four times as many sheep as humans
and consequently, australia is the world's 2nd largest producer of sheep in wool and the 5th largest producer of beef
addition, australia is the home of slightly more than half of all the world certified organic farmland, and as a global leader in almond and lentils production
and best of all, australia's rich culinary culture is heavily represented by the sponsor of this video
hello french. through the delitious recipes, like their sweet and savory pancakes, crumbed pumpkin wedges or lemington style chocolate brownies
and if you're anything like me, you typically struggle a lot to decide what to do at dinner time
should i order expensive takeout, eat on healthy freezer food, or make a time consuming, home cooked meal
i struggled with all of these same decisions for years, until i began using hello fresh, because it's simultaneously healthy, affordable and best of all, quick
now, every week, i select all of the meals that i want on their app and then a box arrives directly on my doorstep with all of the ingredients needed in exactly the right quantities needed
not only is this efficient, less wasteful and better for the environment the traditional grocery shopping is, but it also instantly cuts out all of your shopping time and the majority of your prep time as well, so that you get to focus exclusively on the most fun part, actually cooking
as an example, i just made this incredible pecan crusted chicken, and it took less than 5 min of prep and less than 30 min of actual cooking
all in all. hello. fresh simply makes your meal times better, and that's why i've been using them myself now for years
i'd highly recommend that you try them out as well, which you can do with an insanely great deal when you click the button that's here on screen right now, or by going to hello fresh com and using code real life floor 16 for up to 16 free meals and three additional surprise gifts
it's also a great way to help support my channel, and would really mean a lot
and as always, thank you so much for watching
i-n-t-e-r