california's america's largest, most influential and
most powerful states. with the population near million people
there are more people living in california than in the entirety of canada
and with a total economy size of trillion, california alone would be the world's 5th largest economy, ahead of even the gigantic india, with 35 times the population
the two largest engines inside of california
that fuel all of this economic and population success are greater los angeles, in the south, america's 2nd largest urban area, home to approximately 13 million people, and the san francisco bay area, further to the north, home to approximately eight million more
these are california's two greatest centers of population and financial power, but traveling between both of them has always been a bit of an ordeal
more than 380 mi away from each other, about the same distance as london is from dundee scotland
a typical drive between los angeles and san francisco takes at least 6 h to complete, if not even more, depending on the state of traffic
the only other real alternative choice available is to visit an airport pastor security, board a plane and fly the roughly hour and a half journey between them in the sky
today, so many people choose this alternative that it has become the 2nd busiest flight route over the entire united states
not only are these choices time consuming, expensive and annoying to many, but they're also not exactly ideal for meeting california's increasingly stringent emissions targets
and that's why, beginning back in the late 1990s, the state of california began seriously looking into the feasibility of adding in a better, more sensible 3rd option between the cities, high speed rail, which would be a 1st for the united states
on paper, the concept would make an enormous amount of sense for the states
it would provide significantly quicker transportation between the two big cities than driving, and was supposed to be a cheaper alternative to flying, and with numerous stops along the way that would better connect and serve even more of california's population
the benefits of rapid transit between centers of commerce would be more accessible to more people than ever within the state, with profound economic benefits
and with more people opting to take the train, over flying or driving, california could also work to cut down on their overalls state wide emissions as well
the proposal to begin construction on the rail was passed by california voters 14 years ago, back in 2008
but the trouble ever since then has been that the project is grinding along at a pace that is now dramatically over budget, to the tune of tens of billions of dollars and several years behind schedule
so what's been going on? why has california specifically, and america in general, struggled so much with building a legitimate high speed rail line, while countries of smallest spain have more than 3000 km of high speed rail lines right now
let's get into it. 1st of all, let's talk about the facts on the ground within the united states as they exist today
specifically, there aren't really any high speed rail lines in the country yet
there's technically the acela express that's run by amtrak across the northeast, from washington, d-c to boston, that features america's fastest train speeds of 150 mph, but only across a small stretch of just 34 mi out of the entire 457 mile routes
while most of the high speed part takes place along the 226 mi section between union station and washington d-c and pennsylvania station in new york city
between these two cities, the acila express is capable of running passengers in 2 h and four 45 min while averaging a speed of around 82 mi an hour, when factoring in the various stops along the way
well, perhaps not exactly what comes to mind when imagining true high speed rail, like in japan or europe
it still beats driving between dc and new york by over an hour, and it successfully managed to capture a full 75 % of all the air and trained commuters between the two cities
the essellist service has proved to be a resounding success for commuter travel in the american northeast, and the california high speed rail project is looking to dramatically expand upon that success in the west
the overall plan, as proposed back in 2008, was set to be carried out in two distinct phases
phase one of the plan would aim to link up san francisco in the north, down to los angeles and anaheim in the south, via the central valley, with ten additional stations in between them
once completed, the system would be capable of transporting passengers between san francisco and los angeles at speeds of more than 200 mph in a non stop time of just two 2 h and 40 min and at an advertised cost back in 2008 of only $50 a passenger one way
upon this initial phases, completion, phase two of the line would commence with further extensions, connecting modesto, stocked in in the state capital of sacramento, to the system in the north, along with san bernardino, marietta, as candido, and ultimately san diego in the south, as well, fully connecting all of california's most populous cities and regions together by high speed rail, capable of moving people anywhere else in the system within hours
but the benefits would extend far beyond simply moving people across the state
quicker. back in 2009, the rail authority released projections that the system would ultimately create 450000 permanent new jobs across the state through the increased rates of people commuting into major cities further away than they ordinarily would have without the rail
and for a region like the san walking valley in particular, the benefits of the rail would almost certainly outweigh anywhere else in the states
today, this region is the most impoverished part of california, and it's unfortunately been that way for a long time
a largely rural area, the valleys californias, most substantial contributor to the agricultural and oil industries, and is only a few densely populated clusters of population, like fresno, bakersfield, stockton and merced
however, six of the counties inside of the valley rank as the top six counties in the whole state of california for the high this percentage of residents living beneath the poverty line
and they rank even among the most impoverished counties across the entire united states
of the top five poorest metropolitan areas in the entire united states, three of them are here in the sand walking valley
nearly one in three children living in the value are impoverished
the median household income is 40 % beneath what it is across the rest of the state
and the situation has been constantly evolving since the 1990 as the cost of living in the hugely populated, geographically nearby urban areas like san francisco and los angeles have skyrocketed, more and more, young families and small businesses have been given no other choice than to leave, and many of them have settled in the sand walking valley
thus, major cities in the valley, like stockton, modesto and others, have become increasingly important as commuter cities for working class people into san francisco, while bakersfield has become the same for commuters into los angeles
and thus the population and real estate values within the valley have been increasing for decades, but the area's transportation system hasn't been able to keep up with the pace
and the cow california high speed royal project promises to alleviate a lot of these issues in the community here
not only will it enable commuters to move more quickly to regions with higher paying jobs, like san francisco or los angeles, but it will also bring with it new jobs and opportunities, and the cities that ultimately receive stations, like bakersfield, fresno and mer said, should see increase growth and development prop up around them as well
and by 2080, the initial projections assumed that the system would reduce auto traffic across all of california's highways and roads to such an extent that it would cut down approximately 400 billion mi worth of vehicle travel within the state, which would have obvious environmental benefits to boost
but now, here's the thing all of this was proposed to voters in the state back in 2008 by the california high speed rail authority, an organization that had been set up by the state government twelve years previously, back in 1996
their proposal estimated a total cost of construction for the project at $33 billion and that the 1st trains would begin running by 2020
just twelve years later, $9 billion of state issued bonds were issued to help fund the project, with the rest of the funding expected to come in from the federal us governments and private investors
however, were obviously now in 2022, more than 14 years after the proposition was passed, and two years beyond when service was 1st expected to begin
what's more, the total cost for just the 500 mile long phase one of the system, linking san francisco to los angeles and anaheim, has ballooned nearly threefold from the original sticker price to at least $105000000000 now, already making it the largest single investment in california history and one of america's most ambitious civil engineering projects ever
and the final price is almost certainly going to be even higher than that, because that estimate is based on some old assumptions back from 2019, like an average inflation rate just 3 %
obviously, with annual inflation rates currently running hot and well over 8 %, a lot of these assumptions are outdated, and the final price tag will almost certainly be higher in the end
for context, though, even with the 2019 projections, that is still about one 5th the price of the entire u-s interstate highway system, that expands for a hundred times longer, across nearly 50000 mi, throughout all 50 u-s states and puerto rico, and accounts for a quarter of all vehicle miles driven by all 320000000 plus americans
but it's not only the cost that have been dramatically scaled up for the california high speed rail since being brought to voters back in 2008
construction on this system ever since has focused on building out to the 170 1 mi center across the central valley
1st there will link baker's field in the south with merced in the north
giving commuters the opportunities to
transfer firmers said onto the preexisting altamont corridor, express and sandwalkings, amtrack rail routes
to link to either sacramento or the bay area, and a transfer from baker's
field in the south on amtrax threw way bus service down
however, even this initial central segment is currently not projected to be completed until the end of this decade, around 2029
after it's hopefully completed by then, the next major focus will be on completing the extension in the north towards gilroy and san jose, which includes the southernmost terminus of the already existing cow train, which will ultimately enable high speed trains to finally
run from san francisco down to baker's field
the full completion of phase one, linking san francisco to los angeles and anaheim, is now not expected to be finished any time before 2033, with room for even further delays in the future
and that's not even men the eventual planned extensions towards san diego and sacramento, which at this rate, nobody even really knows about
at the same time, the latest figures for estimated one way ticket prices on the system between san francisco and los angeles are from 2015, and were already inflated up to $86 from the 50 initially advertised voters back in 2008
when adjusted to inflation today, in 2022, that $86 estimate from 2015 is really more like a hundred and $5 now, which is very often even more expensive than just taking a one way flight between the two cities would be
and there have been numerous, numerous setbacks for the project that have been causing all of these issues
one of the most significant is simply the reality of california's geography
there are three major mountain ranges for the rail to eventually cross through, like the southern coast ranges, transverse ranges and peninsula ranges, that specifically require lengthy and expensive tunnels through active seismic zone
and moreover, california has the 2nd highest average real estate prices of any state in the country, making the cost of purchasing an acquiring land for the rail to traverse prohibitively expensive
the project has struggled with acquiring necessary land ever since its inception
but even now, there are still more than 200 parcels of land that the railway needs to acquire in order to capture a 52 mile section in kings county to finish out the central beggars field, tomer said segment, which isn't really good for them, because construction on this route has obviously already begun, and they really need that land at pretty much any price, and the people who own the land can sell it for inflated prices
and thus, as of 2014, the world bank reported that the per kilometer price tag of california's high speed rail system was standing at approximately 56 million dollars, which is freakishly higher than in other countries, like china, where it's more like $19 million, or about one 3rd of the price
even in europe, similar high speed rail projects have only cost between 25 and $39 million per kilometer of track
but the prices in california aren't equal everywhere
part of the reason why the plan was to build the central segment of the high speed rail 1st across the central valley, in the 1st place, widely heckled as the trained nowhere between bakers field and merced, is just because that's simply the cheapest place to actually build out the infrastructure, because the land is pretty much just flat, rural farmland everywhere here, the construction figures are more like 11.4 million /km, which is highly comparable to international prices elsewhere like china or europe
it's only when the rail eventually starts getting into the mountains and the seismically active areas further towards los angeles, san san francisco that the price is truly explode exponentially, and that that's leading a lot of people concerned, because the expected funding that was advertised back in 2008 has also been hard to actually come by in the decade plus since, with construction costs going up and the subsequent cost and ticket prices going up alongside of them, the rails competitiveness with airlines between san francisco and la has been put into question by many private investors, who believe that most californians will ultimately just continue choosing to fly overtaking the rail, especially if flying ends up being cheaper and ultimately ends up being quicker in the end
and it's not just private investment that has been hard to come by either
in 2019, the trump administration canceled nearly 1 billion in federal funding for the railway, setting frustrations over the lack of progress in construction and budget overruns
and last year, in 2021, the much more train friendly, biting administration passed through an infrastructure bill that granted $66 billion to amtrak to further develop the acela express in the northeast and to build out new services elsewhere across the country
but it didn't include any precisely designated funding for california's high speed rail
some sources believe that california may only get as little as $5 billion in funding for the project from the bill, which won't really help all that much with the presently estimated $105000000000 total price tag
there are grave fears among many in california's government that once the central segment between bakersfield and merced is completed at a price tag of around $23 billion, the state will then struggle to find the funding required to finish
out the estimated $5000000000
leg from bakersfield to los angeles, that requires lengthy and expensive mountain tunnels and the estimated
22 billion lay
connecting the central valley to san francisco
if the tens of billions of dollars worth of additional funding can't be found, california may end up being left with what the critics have been slamming the project for all along, an isolated high speed train to know it through the central valley from bakersfield, populations 380000
tomer said, population 80000. and since the funding to ultimately complete the project remains too low, the project has been plagued with ineffective management and no clear guidance from the state governments on what the project's actual next steps are going to look like
and then the covent 19 pandemic certainly didn't do the project any favors, either construction workers currently employed on the project, or at less than half of the numbers they were estimated to be at by this point before the pandemic
overall, if it's ever finished, the california high speed railway could provide enormous potential benefits to the millions of citizens of california
but in order to do so, the project is struggling against the enormous challenges of geography, economics, demographics, america's own cultural and historical preferences for cars and planes, the legal system and more, all of which combine to make the project's ultimate future uncertain
the success or failure of america's 1st truly major high speed rail system is literally hanging in the balance, and it has a ton of catching up to do with the rest of the world
but it be fair, any engineering project like this has its challenges
and if you're anything like me, understanding stem subjects like engineering or math have never come easy
but luckily, we can all get our own little dose of scientific learning from brilliant whether you're looking to learn something completely new, or you're just trying to brush up on a few topics, the best way to learn something is by doing the work yourself, and there is no better place for that than on brilliant
brilliant is an interactive stem learning platform that helps you learn concepts by working through them in a visual, hands on way
and you can get started on any number of courses, for more basic concepts like the physics of the every day and casino probability, to more advanced fields like chemistry and quantum computing, and many more
regardless of which subject it is that you want to learn about, you get to learn at your own pace
you can learn on the go with their mobile app
and most importantly of all, you get to enjoy the rewarding process of understanding things that you never thought were possible before
and if you ever get stuck on a particular question, brilliant never punishes you or impedes your progress
instead, they'll give you an in depth explanation to guide you along your learning path
and best of all, you can try out brilliant right now for free with the link down in the description, or by clicking the button in the here on screen right now
and the 1st 200 people to sign up will also get 20 % off of brilliant premium for a year of stem learning across 2022
and as always, thank you so much for watching