California's america's largest, most influential and most powerful states
With the population near 40 million people
There are more people living in California than in the entirety of Canada
And with a total economy size of trillion
california alone would be the world's 5th largest economy
ahead of even the gigantic India, with 35 times the population
The two largest engines inside of California
That fuel all of this economic and population success are greater Los Angeles
in the South, america's 2nd largest urban area, home to approximately 13 million people
and the San Francisco Bay Area, further to the north, home to approximately eight million more
These are california's two greatest centers of population and financial power
but traveling between both of them has always been a bit of an ordeal
More than 380 mi away from each other, about the same distance as London is from Dundee Scotland
A typical drive between Los Angeles and San Francisco takes at least 6 h to complete
if not even more, depending on the state of traffic
The only other real alternative choice available is to visit an airport pastor security
board a plane and fly the roughly hour and a half journey between them in the sky
Today
so many people choose this alternative that it has become the 2nd busiest flight route over the entire United States
Not only are these choices time consuming, expensive and annoying to many
but they're also not exactly ideal for meeting california's increasingly stringent emissions targets
And that's why, beginning back in the late 1990s
the state of California began seriously looking into the feasibility of adding in a better
more sensible 3rd option between the cities, high speed rail
which would be a 1st for the United States
On paper, the concept would make an enormous amount of sense for the States
It would provide significantly quicker transportation between the two big cities than driving
and was supposed to be a cheaper alternative to flying
and with numerous stops along the way that would better connect and serve even more of california's population
The benefits of rapid transit between centers of commerce would be more accessible to more people than ever within the state
with profound economic benefits
And with more people opting to take the train, over flying or driving
california could also work to cut down on their overalls state wide emissions as well
The proposal to begin construction on the rail was passed by California voters 14 years ago
back in 2008
But the trouble ever since then has been that the project is grinding