this is mexico city
it is currently the 6th largest city in the entire world
with nearly 3 million more people than new york
and it's by far the largest spanish speaking city in the world
mexico city is high on the list of the worlds most significant and influential cities
but it has one enormous and one very old problem
the entire city is sinking into the ground at an insanely alarming rate
with some parts at about half a meter every single year
that is so fast that many geologists have predicted most of mexico city will sink about 20 meters beneath where it currently stands by the end of the 21st centery
with some particularly heavy head areas sinking more than 30 m
imagine your house sinking 30 m beneath where it is today
that would be a hole so deep, if you stood at the top and jumped in
it'd take about two and a half seconds for you to hit the bottom
unfortunately for millions of mexicans
this is exactly what's going to happen to them very slowly over the course of the next few decades
and it's all because humans are really really prone to choosing objectively terrible locations to place their cities in
mexico city, in particular, has some of the worst geography stats of any major city in the world
and this is why
let's rewind the geographical and historical clock back a little over 700 years ago
back then, the region's geography and reality was very different from today
the city didn't exist
and in its place was a large lake called lake texcoco
wedged in a large valley surrounded by high mountains and volcanoes on all sides
legend has it that for a hundred years before this
the nomadic mexico tribe awaited the fulfillment of an ancient prophecy
they would eventually settle down and build the greatest city in the world
where the location would be determined wherever they saw an eagle eating a snake in its beak while perched a top a cactus
eventually, this prophecy would be realized when the mexico finally saw this exact vision
in the most unlikely of places for the greatest city the world would ever see
a small, unpopulated and swampy island right here in the middle of lake texcoco
but undeterred by the formidable terrain
the mexico kept true to their prophecy and began building their great city
and over the next two centuries, this small swampy island was continually enlarged by landfills and floating gardens
until it eventually evolved into tenochtitlan
the capital of the aztec empire and one of the largest cities in the entire medieval world
by the time the spanish arrived in 1519, tenochtitlan was five times the size of london under henry the 8th
and at the time, considering the aztecs position on the tech tree
the city's geography didn't actually seem so bad
without being fortunate enough to have any pack animals like horses or oxen
and without having discovered any practical use of the wheel
the aztecs had no other means available to them for transporting goods and conducting trade then by moving across the water on boats
tenochtitlan's various canals easily facilitated this role
and when you combine that with a complex series of dams they built that provided abundant clean drinking water
extremely rich in fertile soil
and a highly defensible position surrounded by a literal moat
it's no wonder that the city became meso america's most successful
that is, until the spanish and cortes arrived
in 1519, tenochtitlan was put under a brutal siege
and under cortes' direct orders
the aztec dams across the lake were destroyed in order to turn lake texcoco salty
and deny the aztecs inside of any access to clean drinking water
without their drinking water
and after a virulent smallpox epidemic, the aztecs inside withered away
and the spanish conquered and subsequently raised the city almost completely to the ground
brick by brick
by the end of the 16th century
the once great city of tenochtitlan's population had declined by over 90 %
and atop the ruins, the spaniards founded their new settlement, called mexico city
and this is when the big problems really began
the spaniards never rebuilt the aztec dams and dikes
and replace them with more familiar streets and public squares instead
on the plus side
this allowed them to gradually reclaim more and more land from the lake to make more space for mexico cities growing population and buildings
but on the other side
this meant that the city was expanding into a swamp that was surrounded by a lake
without any dam to keep out any of the lakes water
flooding therefore became a constant problem for mexico city as it expanded and grew
including one particularly bad case in 1629, when the city flooded for five straight years
the spanish crown even discussed moving the location of the city to a bit less geographically problematic place
but evidently they thought they just decided to stay and drain the lake even more and even more instead
under the aztecs,  tenochtitlan's population was around 400000 at its peak
and was basically just a small but very dense dot within lake texcoco
by 1900, the population here was actually pretty much the same
but the 20th century would see the city's population absolutely skyrocket
by 1950, the city had grown to cover 30 square miles
and was home to over 3 million people
and today, mexico city has grown from there to cover an area of approximately 3000 square miles
and with nearly 22 million people
this enormous development in just a hundred years has effectively wiped out any trace of the former waters of lake texcoco
and covered it instead with a lake of concrete
and its wreaked total havoc on the valley's environment
mexico cities is in a region that receives even more rain fall in infamously rainy places like london or seattle
but despite that, the city perpetually struggles to provide enough water for her citizens
without the waters of lake texcoco
the city has been forced to drill deeper and deeper into the below ground aquifers in her ever desperate quest for water
the problem here is that the land beneath mexico city is an ancient, soft clay lakebed
at as mexico city drills for more and more water
the clay weakens and crumbles the water pressure within the aquifer's support the soil above it
which in turn supports the city above it
however, as the water is drained and removed, the soil above compacts
this complexion, combined with the lower water pressure pushing from beneath
will slowly cause the city to sink over time
and rainwater can't easily get into the aquifers to replenish them
because the land above is now absolutely covered in the concrete sprawling chaos of the world's 6th largest city
and as a result, mexico city is trapped in a vicious geologic cycle
as the population grows, the demand for water further increases
but without the waters of the natural lake
she has then left with no other choice but to drill deeper into the below ground aquifers
which reduces the soil stability above and leads to the city sinking even further and further
with the increased development above from the increasing population
rainwater can't get in to replenish the aquifers
and the soil's instability continues to get worse
climate change even further exacerbates these already dire conditions
since more heat and more drought in the region inevitably also means more evaporation and even more demand for the already scarce water supply
leading to even further drilling and, of course, even further sinking
mexico city, of course, knows all of this
and through a complex series of canals and pipes
they now import about 40 % of their water supply from other regions of mexico
however, these canals and pipes are wildly inefficient
the constantly shifting elevation causes pipes below the ground to routinely crack and burst
while the struggling city government is rarely capable of mounting any kind of significant repairs
and as a result of that, for every one gallon of water that is pumped into the pipes of mexico city
more than 1/3 of it will simply be lost
and the energy that require to pump all of that water up to a city that's a mile and a half high in elevation in the mountains
is more than what the entire city of puebla consumes
a city with roughly the same population as philadelphia
so as a result
mexico city faces water shortages as if it were in the middle of a desert,
despite receiving more rainfall than london
and there isn't any easy or obvious solution for them to get out of this
but the city's sinking problem affects far more than just the water supply
since it affects some areas worse than others,
roads will suddenly buckle and wobble
buildings tip over and look like they're about to collapse
the metro system in some areas will resemble more of a roller coaster
while the destruction caused by earthquakes is greatly amplified
mexico city is unfortunately located within a seismically active zone
and with most of the city's core located on the weak and silty clay lake bed
the soil will often behave more like a liquid during an earthquake
causing the buildings above to be even more greatly damaged than they otherwise would be
this is how in 1985, the mexico city earthquake caused such catastrophic damage and loss in life to the city
mexico city's rapid and unexpected population explosion in the 20th century caused other unnatural problems to crop up as well
by 1992, mexico city was home to more than 50000 industries and more than 4 million motor vehicles
due to the city's high elevation a mile and a half above sea level
its oxygen levels are 25 % lower when compared to a city that is precisely at sea level
and therefore fuels don't combust as efficiently
for further mexico city is located within a high valley that's surrounded by tall mountains
which effectively keeps pollutants and exhaust trapped within without any place to go
this all meant that by 1992, the un had labeled mexico city as the world's most polluted city
but 30 years later, after a variety of methods
mexico city has managed to get their air pollution levels down in the valley to about the same level scene in los angeles today
but air pollution continues to be the 8th leading cause of death within mexico and causes about one in every 17 deaths in the country
for the aztec seven centuries ago, settling on an island in lake texkoco
not only fulfilled an ancient prophecy
but made perfect geographic sense with their understanding of technology and limited population at the time
in the current day, though
it's one of the worst locations imaginable for the industrialized world's 6th largest city
and has caused countless problems for centuries
but it's too late now, since pushing mexico city somewhere else just isn't really feasible
mexico city's countless geographic problems are just effect of life now
and something that has to be lived with, because in the end, nature will always win
mexico city's struggle against her environment has been one of the most massive and intimidating projects that humanity has had to have ever undertaken