more energy will fall on the world's deserts in 6 h than the entire world will consume over the next year
the sahara desert is well known for being the world's largest hot desert
but it's probably a lot bigger than you even realize
it's nearly the same size as china
it spans across ten different countries in three different time zones
and it gets absolutely massacred by sunlight
this is a map that shows annual sunshine hours across the world
there are some notable hot spots in north america, south america and southern africa
but nowhere gets as much as the sahara desert
most of this china size chunk of land gets more than 3600 h of sunlight a year
within that big chunk is this other chunk that gets more than 4000 h a year
for reference, that's nearly four times the amount of annual sunlight the germany gets
most of this is because the sahara desert is a pretty much directly along the tropic of cancer
which means the sun, for a lot of the year, is pretty much directly over it
and b clouds pretty much never form or even exist over the entire desert
which means all that sunlight is never interrupted
the sahara, consequently
is the best location anywhere on earth to play solar panels and develop solar farms
so it then begs the question, what if we covered the entire desert with solar panels
how much energy would we actually be able to produce
and how would this change our planet
let's take a deep dive
for starters, let's begin here
this is the quarzazate solar power station in morocco
the world's largest concentrated solar power plant currently in existence in a marvel of modern engineering
once fully completed and operational, the plant will take up an area of 25 km² and be capable of producing 582 megawatts of electricity
it will even be capable of storing solar energy in the form of superheated molten salt
which allows for further production of electricity even into the night
after investing more than $9 billion into their solar energy objective
morocco aims to create four additional plants similar to this one in the sahara
that will collectively create more than 2000 megawatts of electricity production
which will be enough to provide for roughly 38% of all of morocco's annual electricity needs
this project will transform morocco into the world's leading solar energy state
and as the only african country that currently has a power cable link to europe
much of this energy will be exported for profit to the countries of the european union
but all of this energy is created from just five relatively small plants
what happens when we scale things up a bit and think bigger
one of the few organizations thinking about sahara solar energy production in the future is the german energy company deserttec
which happens to be an investor of the moroccan solar energy project
according to their research and data taken from the german aerospace center
a solar panel array of just this small size in the sahara could power 100 % of germany's entire electricity needs
an array of this size could power the entire european union
while an array of just this size could power the entire world's modern electricity needs
at approximately 18 trillion watts, give or take a bit
considering that a typical solar panel generates roughly 350 watts of power
this earth powering array would encompass around 51.4 billion solar panels
and it would be roughly the same size as the us state of new mexico, quite a large amount of land
but it's nothing when compared with the vastness of the sahara that also happens to be incredibly sparsely populated
only about two and a half million people live across the sahara
which means that its population density is on a par with siberia
which further means that it's possible to set up huge solar farms like this without too much of a negative impact on the local inhabitants
the desert tech project doesn't quite intend on transforming the entire saharan into a solar farm
but it's still quite ambitious
the general idea to set up a series of massive solar farms across the sahara's perimeter and deeper into the middle east
once constructed
this collection of solar farms will provide for the majority of africas and the middle east electricity needs
while shipping any excess power across cables to europe
that could supply as much as 15 % of the continents in higher electricity needs
this is a real life plan that's undergone significant amounts of research and investment
but why are they only planning on building solar farms around the sahara's perimeter
well
while there's lots of obvious benefits to constructing solar farms in the empty sahara
there's also lots of problems
1st of all, the sahara's emptiness itself is both a blessing and a curse
on the one hand, it means that almost nobody will have to be relocated or moved off of their land
but on the other hand
there isn't any infrastructure to actually get the map massive amounts of supplies into place in any kind of cost effective manner
i mean, look at this map
there's only like four roads that even stretch across the sahara from the north to the south
there are huge empty pockets of land across the desert without a single road at all
and some of these areas, like this northwestern pocket of chad
are more than 600 km kilometers away from the nearest road
transporting billions of solar panels to a remote area like this will necessitate building countless new expensive highways or railroads to get them there
and that's why desert tech is only planning on constructing plants around the sahara
but let's forget all of that for a moment
and just think about the cost of the solar panels themselves in a sahara sized array
a pretty average 350 watt solar panel typically cost anywhere between $250 and $450 once fully installed on a residential roof
today
since we know that it's going to be expensive transporting and installing all of them in the middle of one of the world's most remote locations
we're going to stick with the high cost estimate here and tack on an additional $300 for delivery and infrastructure fees and 250 more dollars for installation fees
conveniently, this math makes the total cost for each 350 watt panel exactly $1000
so from there
you can figure out pretty quickly that the 51.4 billion solar panels needed to fit inside of our new mexico sized array that will power the entire planet cost a cool $51.4 trillion
for reference, that's approximately 60 % of the entire world's gdp
but it would enable us to immediately switch all of our electricity over to renewable solar
so that's pretty cool
all right, then now let's just assume that we've turned on infinite money
and we expanded upon this by filling up the entire sahara desert with solar panels
what is going to happen now
well, for starters, if we assume that the solar panels are 100 % efficient
the entire sahara desert will probably now be producing somewhere around the neighborhood of 1.3 million terawatt hours of electricity per year
so to put that number in a perspective
the entire contemporary human species consumed about 173000 terawatt hours of energy in 2019
and that's not just electricity
that's all energy consumed for everything we did that year
a sahara desert covered in solar panels will generate more than seven times the amount of energy that all of the nearly 8 billion humans of the world collectively consume right now
obviously, this would present revolutionary changes to what mankind could be capable of
and not just even closer to a type one cardishev style civilization
but this overwhelming power given to humanity by harnessing the entire sahara would also come with some significant costs
the black surfaces of the solar panels dotting the sahara will of course absorb most of the sunlight hitting the sahara
only a tiny fraction of that incoming energy will actually be converted into electricity
while the overwhelming majority will be returned back to the environment as heat
in turn
this heat will trigger a sort of feedback loop in which the heat amid by the solar panels would create a steep temperature differential between the land and the surrounding oceans
this will ultimately lower the surface air pressure and cause moist air to rise and condens into clouds and rain across the desert
so by covering the entire sahara with solar panels
will also unwittingly be terraforming the desert sahara into a green sahara at the same time
in some ways, this will be good
because it will open up a massive amount of land the size of china to colonization
human settlement, and, critically, for the emerging economies of north africa
extensive economic development for their countries and their people
but in other ways, this will be really bad
the amazon rainforest
over in south america is extensively fed and fertilized by dust coming over from the sahara that gets blown across the atlantic
while the atlantic ecosystems themselves also benefit from this fertile dust as well
removing all of the sands of the sahara desert could create a cascade of unforeseen events
that could wipe out entire ecosystems in the atlantic, the amazon and probably beyond
and create an epic climate catastrophe, the likes we have never seen before
in summary, covering the entire sahara with solar panels would be epic
but it's also not feasible
it's probably pretty dangerous