venice is one of the world's most wellknown and visited cities with over five and a half million tourists who visited and stayed the night in 2019
venice received 21 times as many tourists as their native population
and despite only being home to about 260,000 people
about the same number as live in lubbock, texas
venice is visited more often than cities that are significantly larger
like moscow, madrid, munich, johannesburg or toronto
to put it into another perspective, during 2019, the city of venice
with a population that's not even 260000 people
received 86% of the same number of overnight tourists as the entire country of brazil did
with a population of over 212,000,000 people
there's just something magical about this small city that's captured the imagination of generations across centuries
perhaps it's the fact that even now, in the 21st century
it's remained the final large urban environment in europe that has survived without cars or trucks and has continued to rely instead upon simple walking and boats
as they have for thousands of years
or perhaps it's the sheer and ancient beauty of the canals and buildings themselves in the city that many consider to be a living museum
full of masterpieces from a bygone era that still speak to our souls today
but unfortunately, both for venice and the world, venice has two massive problems
the entire city is drowning
and too many people are coming to watch it die
these are all video clips that have been taken just in the past few years of a city at war with water
and the water has been getting stronger and stronger
recently, venice has been getting flooded more than 60 times a year
and during the worst of these floods
as much as 80% of the entire city could find itself a little bit underwater
and then there's the number of people coming to see it
before the pandemic shut the world down in 2020
2019 was the peak year for tourism in venice
while five and a half million tourists visited and actually spent at least one night within the city that year
19 million more tourists visited and spent less than a day there
and venice itself is really tiny
it's only about 5 km² in area, with nearly 26 million people visiting in a single year
that means that at any given time in 2019
there was nearly one tourist for every three residents in the city
these problems have been getting worse and worse every year now for decades
but in order to fully understand why this is happening now and what's being done to save the city
you've got to understand some of the city's history
first of all
the strategic location of venice on an island in the center of a lagoon has long offered its security and protection from outside powers
before the fifth century ad
the lagoon itself was a relatively isolated and swampy backwater of the roman empire
but when the huns and germanic peoples began their invasions of the italian peninsula
it generated one of the ancient world's greatest refugee crises
and many of these refugees sought the precious safety that was offered inside of the venetian lagoon
the lagoon is the largest wetland or marshy environment found anywhere around the mediterranean sea
and the dozens of islands scattered across it that rise above the shallow water offered immensely valuable protection across the water from the marauding bands of germans and huns back over on the mainland
and over time
the lagoon itself would become the wellprotected cradle for one of the most powerful and influential civilizations in history
proud of these islands
gradually evolved the absurdly rich venetian republic and her massive maritime commercial empire
the lagoon itself offers multiple advantages for the home base of a maritimebased civilization
the waters around the city provide a natural moat that any would be invaders have to successfully cross first
further
the waters around the city inside of the lagoon are generally calm because it's a shallow bay that's almost entirely enclosed from the rest of the mediterranean sea
with only these three possible entrances from the outside
meaning that the lagoon is a fantastic natural harbor for parking ships
the position of venice
inside of the safety of the lagoon and the position of the lagoon at the very tippy top of the adriatic sea
enabled the city an incredibly safe base of operations from which to build ships in peace and from which to launch them out in war
this geographic advantage enabled the city of venice, over time to dominate the entire adriatic
and from there, over time, the entire mediterranean sea as well
eventually, by the 14th century, the city had constructed the venetian arsenal
a massive shipyard that at its height
took up 15% of the entire city and was the largest industrial complex found anywhere in europe prior to the industrial revolution
by almost independently inventing the assembly line nearly 600 years before henry ford
the venetians were capable of producing fully equipped merchant or naval vessels at a rate of one every day
something that was completely unprecedented anywhere else in the world in the medieval and renaissance eras
through this process, granted by their geographic advantages
the venetians eventually assembled a fleet of more than 3000 ships
which they at first used to completely safeguard their city
surrounded by a moat separated from the mainland
and then to dominate the entire adriatic and mediterranean seas
carving out colonies across the adriatic coast
along with a sizable chunk of greece and cyprus
by dominating the mediterranean
the venetians completely monopolized the flow of trade coming into europe from the east
and with their interesting location just south of the strategic brenner, passed through the alps
they could easily funnel their goods both across italy and north
through the mountains to germany and beyond to the rest of europe
venice's geography all but guaranteed that it would become medieval europe's principal center of commerce and trade
and it quickly became the wealthiest city on the entire continent
but a series of increasingly unfortunate events completely changed the entire calculus of power
first of all, the venetians, all on their own
decided to confront the significantly more powerful and rising ottoman empire and lost against them repeatedly
gradually losing more and more of their colonial possessions across the mediterranean in the process
second
venice's strategic location that enabled it to dominate trade from the east was only as good as the knowledge of the world map
and as the portuguese began exploring more and more of it in the 16th century
they were able to completely undermine venice's prior advantage
venice had spent centuries concentrating on building galleys that were rely upon ores
the perfect ships for moving across the calm waters of an inland sea like the mediterranean
but pretty terrible for moving across the unpredictable and often harsh waters of the open ocean
venice was unable to adapt and therefore became locked inside of the mediterranean and missed out on the european rush for colonies across other continents
and when the portuguese discovered the cape of good hope for the europeans
their larger and more ocean worthy ships ended up dominating the indian ocean itself
and the trade from the east shifted towards portugal and other powers from there
forever destroying venice's prior monopoly and the source of her vast wealth
venice's influence waned and waned across the following centuries
until venice itself was conquered by the french and then passed back and forth between them and the austrians for a while before finally becoming a part of the modern nation state of italy itself
for more than five centuries now
since vasco da gama discovered the cape of good hope and opened up the indian ocean directly to european trade
venice has never again managed to regain its prior historical significance
and now, today, in the 21st century
the city is facing these new modern crises that threaten its entire existence once again
let's begin with a flooding issue
obviously, a city that's literally surrounded by water, like venice
will have a flooding problem from time to time, much like new orleans in the united states
but venice is located in a uniquely flood vulnerable area
it's located in the lagoon at the very top of the adriatic sea
while the adriatic's long, narrow
and rectangular shape amplifies the natural tides moving up it
meaning that the adriatic naturally has substantially more extreme tidal events than the rest of the mediterranean does
and the adriatic pretty much funneled them all up right towards venice
further
the strong northbound winds in the area whipping off the adriatic blow directly towards the three connections between the lagoon and the sea
which can significantly slow down or even totally block the water outflow from the lagoon into the sea
and when that happens, the ebb of water is blocked inside of the lagoon
and the next high tide that comes in overlaps with the previous one
which just kind of perpetuates this vicious selfsupporting cycle of flood
and to make matters even worse, venice is located atop the adriatic tectonic plates
which is currently in the process of shifting beneath the italian coast
meaning that venice is naturally sinking and losing elevation in an area that's already highly prone to flooding
but in addition to these natural problems, humans have, of course
been making even more manmade problems for themselves as well
had the venetian lagoon simply been left to itself into nature over the past thousand years
it probably would have completely filled up with silt by now
because of the various major sediment rich rivers that used to flow into it
and venice would have been more or less loosely connected to the mainland
the medieval venetians were well aware of this problem and unwilling to allow venice's greatest offensive asset to be destroyed like this
they began diverting the rivers away from the lagoon to keep the sediment out and to keep venice enclosed by water
over time
this made the waters inside of the lagoon deeper and deeper and increased the scale of venice's moat and therefore increase their safety from the mainland
but it also made flooding of the city itself worse as well, because, well
you know, there was just a higher volume of water around it
and then in the 19th century
the italians built a railroad bridge that connected venice over to the mainland
and this was even further expanded in the 1930s by the construction of a road bridge alongside of it
all of which significantly modified the natural motion of the water inside of the lagoon
and in the 20th century
the italian government created an industrial district immediately behind venice
and it made the flooding problems even worse
previously to the industrial district's construction
the area was covered by several small islands just above sea level that acted pretty much like natural sponges whenever high tides came in
but the government completely destroyed them by filling the entire area in to cover it all up for industry
and to make matters more worse
a navigable channel was dug across the lagoon that allowed large modern oil tankers to reach the new industrial district
this artificial channel directly connected the lagoon with a sea
which obviously didn't exist at the time of venice's foundation thousands of years ago
and it's just become another entry point for high tides and storm surges coming into the lagoon from the adriatic
modern studies have indicated that venice is still sinking at a rate of about one to 2 millimeters per year
and over the past decade, global sea levels were rising at a rate of about 3.6 millimeters per year
meaning that venice's actual sea level rise is above the global average because of their sinking problem
back when modern flooding records of venice began in 1872
there was only one severe flooding event before 1950 in the city where the water reached a height of 1.4 meters above sea level
from 1950 until today, however
which is nearly an equivalent amount of time
there have been 21 of the severe flooding events recorded
with more and more happening every new decade
of the top ten highest floods measured in venice since records began
four of them took place in 2019
and the biggest of them in november, was so large
it covered more than 80% of the city and damaged multiple cultural heritage sites
in fact, the centerpiece of venice, st
mark square now regularly floods more than 60 times a year
which way back in 1900, only happened four times
so now, in the 21st century
venice's ambitious plan to fight back against the ocean in geography is called the mandy losterer metal hormones system
essentially
this is a huge system that's designed to hold back the rising tides of the adriatic during high tide in order to better protect the city
and after multiple delays, it's finally nearly finished
the system consists of several rows of large gates located at each of the three natural inlets that lead into the venetian lagoon
with a majority of the gates located at the lido inlet closest to the city of venice itself
there are 78 of these gates in total across all three of the inlets that are each around 20 meters wide and up to 30 meters in length for the deepest sections
under normal tidal conditions
the gates will remain full of water and rest within their respective housing structures down on the sea floor
but whenever a high tide coming in from the adriatic is forecasted in
the lagoon needs to be defended
the gates will rapidly be drained of water and filled up with compressed air
so they shoot back up to the surface and then stop the tide from surging into the lagoon
and then, once the high tide is over with
the gates will once again be filled up with water and return back down to the sea floor below and allow boats and the natural flow of water above to move about
the ultimate goal here is to leave the gates open as much as possible and allow the natural rhythm between the lagoon and the sea to continue and to only raise them up when absolutely necessary
but the system has not come without controversy
for one thing, the schedule and costs have been severely overblown
when it was initially proposed, mos was supposed to be a ten year project and cost 4.2 billion euros
construction began way back in 2003
and it's expected to finally finish only now, at the end of this year
in 2021, more than eight years behind schedule and more than 1.3 billion euros over budget
back in 2014, 35 people, including the then mayor of venice
were all arrested by the italian police on corruption charges in connection with the mos project
multiple environmental groups, including the world wildlife foundation
have repeatedly made negative comments about the project
and while the supporters of mos claim that it will be capable of handling the threats of rising sea levels from climate change
many others doubt it
while the gates could always just theoretically be raised to block out rising sea levels
they could only do so by raising the gate so often that they probably just end up functioning more as a near permanent wall
by being raised nearly all of the time
the lagoon's natural drainage and interchange with the adriatic sea will be completely destroyed
and the lagoons surrounding venice will inevitably become just a gross stagnant pool of garbage and algae
unfortunately, though
that may be the only possible solution that exists to save venice
it's been estimated before that just a 50 centimeter rise in sea levels will pretty much permanently doom venice beneath the waves
and in 2019
the famous ipcc report projected a rise of 600 to 1100 centimeters in sea levels by the year 2100
if greenhouse gas emissions remain the very same as they are today, by the end of this century
venice is probably either going to become the 21st centuries atlantis
or it's going to be stuck inside of a blocked off and stagnant lagoon that's full of algae and trash
and there doesn't really seem to be many good alternative third choices
and throughout all of this
the pace of tourists coming to visit the already drowning and crowded city isn't seeming to go down either
despite the global pandemic
with pent up global demand for international travel at an all time high
the number of tourists who will visit the city in 2025 is projected to soar toward 38 million people
a number that many venetians consider to be grossly unsustainable
that would mean on an average day in 2025
there would be nearly one tourist for every two residents in the small five square kilometer city
these extremely high levels of overtourism are creating overcrowding and even further environmental problems for the ecosystem around the fragile lagoon
the entire city of venice and its lagoon are considered a world heritage site by unesco
and because of its rampant over tourism
unesco was considering placing the city on its endangered list
which usually only includes historical ruins in war torn countries like syria or iraq
earlier in june of 2021
unesco narrowly avoided placing venice on the list because the italian government finally banned the passage of large cruise ships entering in through the city's historic center
but that's pretty much just a minor step in solving venice's tremendous problems
in the end
all of the engineering and policies in the world may not be enough to match the overwhelming firepower that nature is bringing to venice this century
i think that ultimately saved for taking venice and pushing it somewhere else
i'm not really certain about venice's future
and neither is anybody else, because in the end
no amount of technology can possibly overcome the fact that venice is located on a chain of sinking islands in the middle of a marshy lagoon
and the water that surrounds it from the outside gets higher and higher